Hello and welcome to Section 8 security and authentication in this section we're going to be continuing
on with the to do API turning it into a more real world application by adding user accounts.
Up until now anybody could come in and manage to do is created by anybody else I could go in and wipe
everyone's data.
And there's nothing they could do about it.
Once we add user accounts we're going to be locking down that data.
You're only going to be able to do anything with the news when you're logged in.
You only see to news you create it and you can only update the dues that you created.
Now in order to do all this we are going to look at some advanced Mongo DB and Mongoose topics and we're
also going to look at some security topics like hashing encryption and Jason Webb tokens all of this
is coming up in this section.
But let's get started by creating our user model