Now that we have the log in or out in place the goal for this video is to write two test cases for it.
We're going to write one that makes sure when a valid e-mail password combo is sent we get an x Aalto
can back and we're going to write a second test case that makes sure if the log in credentials don't
match a user in the database we return a 400.
Now before I do any of that I am going to remove this comment right here.
This is left over from the challenge in the previous video.
Now I can save the server file and we can move into the server test file head to the bottom and add
a new.
Describe a block for this route describe this block of tasks will be for post forward slash users a
forward slash log in then we can set up our aero function we'll have our two test cases the first test
case we're going to do together it should log in user and return auth token.
This is when we have a valid email and password as the request body we can set up our function with
our Done argument.
And now we can go ahead and define the second test case and this is the one that you're going to be
doing as a challenge.
It should reject invalid loggin this test case is going to make sure that if something goes wrong like
the password doesn't match the user's password the logon is indeed rejected.
We're going to knock out the first test case together and the second one that will be your challenge
for the video.
Now in order to make either of these requests we are going to need access to the seed data for this
first test case.
I'm going to go ahead and use the second user's e-mail and password and then we can go ahead and query
this user inside of the database.
After the call comes back and make sure the token was added to get started with that I am going to call
request passing in the application and we will be making a post request to forward slash users forward
slash loggin.
Now we can set up the body data we want to send which in our case is the email and the password.
We have access to the email property via the user's array.
We're gonna grab that second user using the index of one and we'll grab his e-mail and we can do the
exact same thing for the password.
I'm going to set password equal to we're going to go into that user's array.
Grab the first item and grab the password property.
Now a decent place at the request has been successfully set.
We have a valid e-mail and password.
We have the right HTP method and you R-AL which means now it's time to make some assertions.
First up the easy ones.
Let's expect a 200 to come back as the status which it will be if everything goes as planned.
And we can make an assertion that verifies an X auth token was sent back as a header.
I'm going to expect using a custom expect function inside of here we will expect that the response headers
object has an X or token will use bracket notation.
Once again since we have a hyphen in our property name and we're going to expect this value to exist
then the next thing we can do is call and and this is where we're going to set up our custom asynchronous
function which is going to go ahead and query the database.
I'm going to call end passing in the custom function which gets called with a potential error and the
response.
And like all of the cases where we used a custom function in and the first thing we're going to do is
check for errors if there are errors.
There is no reason to continue.
We can simply return by calling down and passing in the error.
So it gets properly printed to the screen.
Now if there are no errors with the assertions up above we are going to need to find the user that we
potentially created a token for using user and we can query it using find by ID since we already know
the idea of the user it's sitting right here.
Next up I can go ahead and pass in that ID.
I'm going to go ahead and access the first item in the user's array grab that id property just like
this.
And we can tack on a then call back to do something when the user query finishes.
Now if it finishes what we want to do is assert that the token that came back was indeed added into
the tokens array.
Let's expect that the user has a tokens array and that's the first item includes using to include the
following actual butes.
Now we have used to include before it doesn't mean it equals.
It means that the tokens object that first item has at least these properties.
We need an access property equal to off and we need a token property equal to the token we got sent
back.
That's in response headers object.
And we can use bracket notation to get the value for x off.
Now this is our assertion inside of the query and we are all done which means we can call done like
our other asynchronous tasks.
We also want to tack on a catch call back to catch the error that might occur right here.
If they're not equal on an add a catch call we're going to get the error and we're simply going to pass
it in to done just like this.
Now this is something that we've done for most of our queries.
When we pass a custom function in to end.
But if you notice up above for sign up we did not do that right here.
All I'm going to do is copy the line from below the highlighted code right here.
Move up to the test case for we forgot to add it.
It should create a user and paste it right here.
Now with the test case still fail if one of these assertions failed.
You betcha it's going to look for a catch case.
It's never going to find one which means Dunn doesn't get called and the test will time out but you're
not going to get a useful error message.
By adding this you're going to get the exact error message depending on which assertion failed and why
it failed.
Now that we have this in place our test case is complete with our custom query in place we can go ahead
and save our test file and run the test suite from the terminal.
I'm going to use NPM test to start up the test suite we're first going to move through our to do related
tasks.
Eventually we'll get to our get users test which is coming up next.
And our Sign-Up test all of those test cases are passing.
Here is our loggin test.
It did indeed pass which is fantastic.
Now the second test case failed because I haven't filled it out.
That's perfectly fine as long as you're.
Should logon user and return auth token test as passing.
You are ready to move on.
Now if one of these values did not match to include would throw a proper error and to prove that I can
simply change auth to off t.
This proves that that is essential to make sure to add this catch call if you don't call it you're not
going to get a clear error message which is just going to make your life a lot harder.
You're gonna have to dig around and figure out exactly why things are not working as expected this time
around.
We do get an error and it's really clear we expected some object to include these values.
These values obviously were in that object and we can go right to the source to figure out why.
Now that we're done with the first test case let's go ahead and move on to the second one and this is
going to be your challenge.
This test case is going to be really similar to the one we just created.
The only thing you're going to change is instead of passing in a valid password you're going to pass
in an invalid password and then you're going to tweak all of your assertions.
The 200 should be a 400.
You should expect the X auth token to not exist.
And down below you should expect that the user tokens array has a length equal to zero because no token
should have been created and it didn't have any to start with.
So the length should still be 0.
Take a moment to knock this out.
You can actually copy the contents of the test case up above.
Paste it into the test case down below tweak it then rerun the test suite make sure everything passes
and if it does you're good to go.
Pause the video.
Knock this out.
Test it.
And when you're done click play.
All right.
I'm going to get started by copying the code from up above and pasting it down below.
Then we can tweak it to fit what this test is supposed to test.
I'm going to change the password to anything other than what it is by concatenating some value.
The number one will do the trick.
And then we can go ahead and tweak the assertions.
The 200 should turn into a 400.
We should not get an x or token.
So I'm going to use to not exist.
And down below instead of expecting the first item to include certain properties we're going to expect
that the array itself has a length equal to zero which means we can remove the entire to include call
and replace it with one to be 0 just like this.
And that's all it takes.
Tweaking this test case really isn't too bad.
And if we now rerun the test suite we should see all of the test cases passing.
This will be the final time we rerun it for this video so you'll only have to watch these test cases
go through just this once.
Here we go we are nearing the end Rathi sign up call.
Now we're at the loggin call all of our test cases are passing which is fantastic.
All of the tweaks to our test case do appear to be working which means we are done.
We can make a comment and wrap this one up.
I'm going to run and get status and we should have those two changed files.
We made a small tweak to server and we added a few tests to the server test file get commit with the
AM flag we'll add those to the next commit ad tests for post users logon.
I'm going to make the commit.
Push it up to get how and that is it for this one.
I will see you in the next video where you are going to explore how to log out users.
This means we'll be deleting all tokens as opposed to creating them.
It's coming up next.
So stay tuned.
We'll see you then