In this video we're going to add our final authentication related call it's going to be a call to log
out a user which means it is going to be a call that requires authentication we can't lock someone out
unless they're logged in and all we're going to do is remove the token from the tokens.
Right.
First up let's define the route.
It's going to be a delete route since we're trying to remove something so I'll call app delete to register
it and the you are all for this one is going to be forward slash users forward slash me bored slash
tokin.
We're trying to delete the token off of the currently logged in user.
Now you're not going to need to pass the token value in via the body or some sort of you or L parameter
instead we're just going to make this route private which means you're going to have to be authenticated
in order to ever run the code.
And if you remember inside of our authentication middleware we store the token used right here for Quest's
token equals the token.
So we'll be able to grab that token value out later to add authentication.
All we have to do is specify the authenticate middleware just like we did for our other private route.
And there we go.
That is all that we have to do.
Now we can add our callback with a request and response argument we can finish off our aero function
and in here we're going to actually write the code to delete the token and that was used inside of the
authentication middleware to actually remove the token.
All we're going to do is call a method.
We have to define that method but in here in a server as well we're going to do is call an instance
method we have access to the user via Everquest dot user since they're authenticated and we can call
an instance method by calling it right here.
We're going to make one called remove tokin never move token is going to need to know which token you
want to remove but that's fine.
We also have that information it's stored on request a dot token.
And before we actually fill out this function Let's go ahead and figure out what we want it to do in
terms of response and then we can go ahead and actually write the code.
Ideally it would return a promise because we're going to need to respond to the user once the token
has been deleted.
We can attach a then call back right here.
We don't need any data back.
We just need to know when the token was deleted so we can respond response status 200 dot send is going
to get the job done there.
And if things don't go well for some reason we'll respond with a 400 inside of our second call back
to then this is going to fire if there's any errors response status 400 and we're going to send that
back as well.
Now that we know how we want to use the removed token method let's go ahead and actually define it over
inside of user.
Yes.
I'm going to scroll down and this is going to be an instance method.
So I'll define it right below our last instance method.
This one will be on user schema like our other instance methods have been.
We're going to go on to the methods object and we're going to create remove tokin never move tokens
as we just discussed is going to need an argument.
It is going to need the Tokin to delete just like this and we're going to do is call the update method
to update our array.
Now we have this array of tokens.
We defined it right here.
What we want to do is remove any object from the array that has a token property equal to the value
that we passed in in order to get that done we're going to be using a really awesome Mongo DB operator.
It's called dollar sign.
Paul Paul lets you remove items from an array that match certain criteria to take a look at how this
works.
We are going to make a variable called a lowercase you user since this is an instance method and we'll
set it equal to this and then down below we can go ahead and call user dot update user data update.
Doesn't take a query.
We already have the user We're updating all we do is pass in the updates object right here.
We're going to use the pull operator and the pull operator gets set equal to an object.
And on here we can define what we want to pull from.
We're going to pull from the tokens array I specify tokens and we're going to pull any object on the
array that has a token property equal to the token argument passed here.
So if this token doesn't match anything in the array it's not going to remove anything if the token
does match something in that array is going to get removed not just the token property of the entire
object which means the object with the id the access property and the token property.
That means there'll be one less item in the array.
Now I am going to return this.
This is going to let us chain together our call that we already set up over inside of server jacks right
here.
And with this in place we are done.
There really isn't a heck of a lot to do when it comes to removing a token.
I can simplify this even further.
I have a property name equal to a variable with the same name which means right here I can just specify
token like this.
Now that we have this in place let's go ahead and test things out over inside a postman and see what
happens when we make a request to log out a user before I make any requests to go ahead and wipe my
database once again so I can start fresh if I refresh it I can see I do indeed have a to do app database.
I'll go ahead and drop it.
Then I can start up my server over inside of the terminal node server forward slashes server.
Yes once the server is up and running.
I'm going to head into post man make a user using the post user's request and the default data works
just fine.
I'm going to send off this user and I do get a 200 back.
Which means that a user was successfully created and I also had that X auth token.
Now to prove that the X auth token was actually saved inside of the database I'm going to go ahead and
open up the user's collection.
I'm going to refresh to reveal the new database then we can go ahead and expand it.
Grabbing the users collection and viewing all of those documents inside here we have our one user and
there is indeed one token with the token value of the X or token we just got back.
Now let's go ahead and try and remove this completely inside of post man.
I'm going to grab this X auth token value copy it to the clipboard and make a brand new request.
This is going to be a delete request.
We're going to use the same base you are al the rest of the path is forward slash users forward slash
me forward slash tokin then I can go ahead and set up the proper header which is the X hyphen off Hetter
and I'm going to set it equal to the value of the token.
I just create it if I send this off.
What do we get.
We get a 200 back and if I go into Roboam mango we can go ahead and refresh the users collection one
more time.
We still have our user but this time there are no elements inside of the tokens array.
And this is fantastic.
Now if I try to make the exact same request inside of postman again we're going to get a 401.
Authorized because this token no longer exists and you have to be logged in in order to make this request
with the request set up and working.
I'm going to go ahead and save it to our collection so we can easily make it later on.
Let's save this one as changing the name to delete followed by the you are l and I'm going to add it
to our existing to do app collection perfect.
With that in place we are done with our alog out call.
We'll be testing it in the next video but for now we can go ahead and make a commit saving our changes.
I'm going to run and get status and we have our two changed files as expected.
I can run it get commit with the name and flag and right here.
I'm going to go ahead and specify the message add delete the users me token route.
I'm going to make that commit.
Push it up to get help.
And that is it for this one.
I will see you in the next video where we test our final route from there on out will be integrating
the user collection with the to do collection.
Stay tuned.
I will see you soon