Now that you have your log out route in place it's time to go ahead and test this by adding a new describe
black at the very bottom of our server test file.
We're going to verify that when we send a cross a token.
It does indeed get removed from the user's collection over at the bottom of server test.
Yes we can out our final describe block for our final route.
We're going to call the scrod passing in the route signature.
It's a delete route and the you are Alice forward slash users forward slash me forward slash token exactly
as we have it right here.
Next up we can add our function and then here we're going to add one test case that you're going to
be responsible for filling out this test case.
It's going to make sure that when a real valid X or token gets passed across to the log out method it
actually does get logged out.
It should remove auth token on log out.
This is going to be an asynchronous function so I'll specify done right here and to get this done.
We're going to need some seed data and we actually already have some good data in our database for this
test case right here.
Our first user they already have a tokens array which means that we can just grab this token value.
Use this as our X auth token.
Then after the fact we can make sure that the database was updated and that the tokens array has a length
of 0.
To summarize the first thing you're going to do is make a delete request to the users me token.
You're also going to set X off equal to token.
This is going to be the token inside of the tokens array right here.
Then you're going to go ahead and make some assertions.
You're going to expect that you get a 200 back then you're going to add an asynchronous and call like
we do here to make an asynchronous assertion here you're going to find a user in the database find user
and you're going to verify that tokens are has a length of 0.
Once you have all of this in place you can go ahead and run the test suite from the terminal and you
should see a new test showing up and it should be passing.
Feel free to use Google or anything we've done in this course including the current file to get this
done.
We have done everything you need to do here.
Up above somewhere in the server test file.
Pause the video.
Knock this out and when you're done click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to get that done without too much trouble to get started.
We are going to be making a request to our application and this is going to be a delete request so I
will call the delete method now the route for this one is going to be a regular out there is no need
to inject any u r l parameters so we can use a regular string and specify it forward slash users forward
slash me forward slash token.
Now the next thing that we need to do is set the X auth header because remember this route is not only
private but it uses that token as the token to delete right here inside of the server test file we can
use set as we've done previously to set X off equal to the value we want to use.
Now in our case we do want to use that user's seed token value.
We're going to grab the first user then we'll grab the first token let's go into the user's array and
grab the very first user then we're going to access the tokens array property grabbing the first token.
And finally we're going to access the actual token value with this in place.
We're actually done making the request and now we can start making our expectations and assertions first.
We're going to expect that we get a 200 back then we're going to add a custom call back to end like
we've done before we'll specify the error and response arguments and inside of here the first thing
we'll do as always is handle the error if there is any error from the assertions above all we're going
to do is return Garling done passing the error to the done function.
Now we can make our custom assertion which means that we're going to want to query the database first
up I'm going to use user and not find a by ID then I'm going to pass the ID in of the first user which
I have access to the users.
Going to grab the first user and I'm going to access the D property.
Next up we can go ahead and add are called to then so we can do something when that user comes back
right here.
I'll add my function where we get that the user document and we can make our assertion about what's
inside of the database.
Now in this case the only thing we're going to assert is that the user tokens array has a length of
zero.
Expect user ADOT tokens ADOT length to be 0.
Now that we have our one assertion in place we can go ahead and call done wrapping up the test suite
and I can add a call to catch to catch any errors that might occur.
Printing them to the screen correctly right here we're going to call done passing in the error argument.
With this in place I'm going to go ahead and remove the comments up above and we can go ahead and run
the test suite from the terminal by running.
NPM test.
Now once you get to the very bottom of our test file we should see our delete token out and the test
case should be passing.
If it is we are all done testing our routes and we can move on to start the integration right here where
we create users route here's our delete route and the test case is indeed passing.
We're expecting the length to be zero.
If the length wasn't zero for example if it was one the test case would indeed fail because the value
that we expect does not equal the value actually inside of the database.
Now that we are done we can go ahead and wrap this video up by making a commit to save our changes right
here inside of the terminal in just a second.
We're going to see the test case fails.
I'm going to revert that change and now we can go ahead and make it commit.
I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output and run get status to see the changes we have here.
We just have changes to our server test.
J.S. fine.
Now aside from using a GUI like source tree which is a graphic user interface for managing get we can
always run get diff.
And this is going to let us see the changes to the file.
Here you can see we have a lot of green lines which means these are additions to the repository.
And what do we have in green.
The code we wrote in this video everything looks great which means that we can make it commit get commit
with the.
And the flag or the combined am flag.
Both do the exact same thing.
And you can message for this one as add tests for delete forward slash users forward slash me forward
slash tokin.
With this in place I can make the commit and push it up to get help.
And we are done in the next couple of videos.
We're going to be integrating the users and to do it together.
So when you created to do the user ID is associated with that to do and only that user can manage that
to do.
Currently inside of server J.S. all of the to do related routes are still public.
They don't require authentication and we don't care who created that to do.
We're simply going to return it regardless.
All of that is getting fixed.
Coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you next time.