All of our routes are complete it's time to start making it to do route's private and only letting users
manage the dues they've created.
Now in order to get started we're going to need to make a change to the to do model currently we store
the text the completed value and the completed at time stamp what we're going to also need to store
is in the ID of the user who created that to do.
This is going to let us make sure the user does indeed have access to manage this data.
Now to get started.
Down below after the completed at options object we're going to make a brand new one called underscore
creator.
Now you could call this property anything you want.
I'm using the underscore to let the person who's using the model know it is an object id and the creator
seems like a good name because it stores the ID of the user who created it.
Next up we can go ahead and specify a few quick options.
We are going to require this.
So I will set required equal to true.
You're no longer going to be able to make a to do unless you have an ID which means you're logged in.
The other option we're going to specify is the type.
Now in this case the type is going to be an object ID in order to set a type equal to an object ID.
We're going to go into mongoose.
We're going to access schema which we've used inside of the users file then we're going to go ahead
and access the types object and on there there is a type Object upper case I lowercase D.
This is what we need to set our type to in order to set up the Creator property.
From here we can now save the to do model file and head into our test see data inside of here.
We currently have two to do.
These are the seed to do we add to the database.
They're available in our test cases.
The problem is they're not associated with the user but we're going to do a set creator for both for
the first to do.
I'm going to set underscore creator equal to the object idea of the first user which we have access
to via user one ID user one ID.
Perfect and we're going to do the exact same thing for the second to do item down at the very bottom
below completed at.
I'm going to add underscore creator and for this one will set the ID equal to user to ID.
Now when we run the test suite we'll be able to access the users to Dewes because we've associated each
to do with a real user.
Now the first route that you are going to convert is the post to do's route.
This is the route that creates new to do.
Currently when we make art to do we set the text equal to the body text.
We also need to set the creator property right here.
Now in order to make this route private as we know we have to add the authenticate middleware end with
this in place we now have access to the user and the token that was used.
All of that is configured over inside of the authenticate middleware right here.
That means inside of our post to Dewes route we can now set to create a property when we make our new
to do right here.
I'm going to set underscore creator equal to the request user property and then we're going to go ahead
and grab the idea.
This is the ID of the user.
And there we go.
Our post to Doo's route has been successfully updated.
Honestly not too bad.
Now before we go any further we're also going to tweak the get to do's route then we can go ahead and
verify that all of this works as expected.
Forget to do's.
We're going to also add that authenticate middleware.
This is going to require that an X auth token is used when you're fetching to do's and instead of thatching
all to do is we're simply going to fetch to do's.
We're going to try to queery and we're going to look for to Dewes where the underscore creator property
equals the ID of the user that is currently authenticated request user underscore ID.
Now we're only going to be returning to Doo's that the user who's logged in actually created.
Which means that if user one adds some to Doo's user 2 is not going to be able to view them when they
try to fetch all of the to do's.
It's no longer all the to do is listed in the database.
It's now all the to do's for the currently logged in user.
I'm going to go ahead and save server JSC and we can start up our project over in the terminal.
I'm going to use gnomon to startup the file in the server directory called server.
J.S. once our server is up on port three thousand we can go ahead and move into post-mission fire off
both of these requests and see exactly what happens.
First up I am going to wipe the data in robo mango since we've added some new properties.
I can simply drop the to do app database then over inside a postman we can get started by signing up
a user for it here.
I'm going to go ahead and sign up a new user using my default body data.
This is going to give us an X auth token and that token is going to be used to make the two requests
right here.
I'm going to grab the X auth token value making sure to copy the entire thing.
I'm going to copy it to the clipboard and we'll get started by creating a new do using POST forward
slash to do's inside of the headers for the call we are going to need to add a new one the X or header
X hyphen off and then we'll paste the X or token in as the value.
Next up that we can go ahead and send this request off when we do.
What do we get.
We get a 200 back.
Meaning that everything went as expected and down below we have our to do we have R-TX property we have
our Creator ID we have the underscore ID property completed at and completed.
This is fantastic.
Now when we make a to do the exit off token is used to fetch the user and the user's ID is stored right
here.
If I were to go ahead and wipe the X or token value and try to create a another to do we're going to
get a 401.
Unauthorized.
Now the next thing we need to test out is that when we fetch to do's we only get the dues back for the
user we created to do this.
I'm going to sign up a second user.
Mean many as post users I'm going to create Andrew to add example dot com.
Send that off and I'm going to copy this X Auth. hetter inside of my clipboard.
Make sure to grab the entire thing from the beginning to the very end sometimes it goes off the screen.
Sometimes it wraps to a second line.
Now that they have the X auth token value we can make a new to do using post to Duse I'm going to go
ahead and set the X off.
Heather equal to this value we're going to send it off and we get our to do.
Back now when we called get to choose with the author value we should only see one to do coming back
even though there's two in the database because the second to do the one we won't see was created by
a different user.
Right here we'll set X off equal to the token for the second user.
We're going to send off the request and what do we get back.
We get back just one to do item.
If we open up robo mango though and we refresh to see the database we dropped we will be able to see
that there are indeed two documents inside of the two do's collection.
Right here we have the two but we're only able to see one because we've made it private.
Now since we've made these routes private our test cases are going to fail if we head into the terminal
and try to run the test suite using NPM test.
We're going to see that we get a lot of 401.
On authorized because the test cases they're not specifying an X off Hetter.
So when we try to fire off the requests to create to do's and fetch to do's you can see right here we
expect to hundreds.
But we get 4 0 ones back in order to fix this.
All we have to do is make some small tweaks to the contents of our server test file up at the very top
our first to describe blocks are for the two routes we just changed.
Here we have our test cases for post to do's and down below.
We have our test cases for get to do's we're going to go ahead and update these to use the proper authentication
mechanisms.
First up the very first test it should create a new to do here we need to specify an X auth token value
using the set method.
We're going to set X hyphen off equal to the value we have over in the data we're going to go into the
users array.
We're going to grab the first user then we're going to go into the tokens a grab the very first token
and access that token property with the token in place.
This test case is now going to pass all of the assertions we make below are not going to be affected
by this change we'll still expect the body to have a text property equal to the text we set.
And when we find that to do inside of the database we're going to expect that the text also equals the
text we set.
Nothing needs to change here.
The next test case is going to be pretty similar.
It should not create to do with invalid body data.
We're going to need to set the X off Hetter value.
I'm going to go ahead and copy the line up above by adding it to the clipboard and pasting it down below
just below our call to post.
Now we're passing along a valid X auth token.
We're going to go ahead and try to make the request to create an invalid to do and at the very end we
expect that the total number of documents in the dues collection should be two and that is still valid
regardless of who created it.
We have to see it to do's in the database.
Now the next test is going to be a little different.
This is our test for getting all that to do is the get forward slash to Dewes route.
We're still going to set up the X auth Hetter but we are going to need to make some changes to our expectation
down below.
Currently we expect that we're going to get to Dewes back but we know that's no longer the case now
that the dues are associated with the users we're going to get just one to do back.
We have one to do where the creator property is set to the ID for the first user.
That means over inside of server tasks.
We're going to change this two to a one which is the correct number of dues that should get returned.
Now that we have our test cases updated for the routes we made prior that we can go ahead and rerun
everything in the test suite.
Now it's fine if some of our other tests fail because of these changes.
As long as the three tests we just tweaked pass we are good to go and right up top you can see just
that happens both of our posts to Doo's.
Tests are passing and our get to Doo's case is indeed correct and that's fantastic.
We've now converted a few of our to do routes and the next video we're going to convert the final ones
wrapping up the process of associating users with to Dewes.
Let's take just a quick moment to summarize how we did this.
The first thing we needed to do was update the to do model if they to do is going to be associated with
a user We need a way to set up that association and that happens right here on the to do we store the
ID of the user later on we can go ahead and verify that a user created that to do just by checking this
property.
Now once we created this property we also went ahead and added authentication to both of these routes.
This means that we have access to the user and the token right inside of the request call back and we
can do stuff like this where we set the creator property equal to the ID of the logged in user or something
like this where we fetch all the dues but we only return the ones where the creator property equals
the ID of the currently logged in user by adding authentication using the middleware and by using the
ID inside of our queries we're going to be able to make the to do's private now that we have this in
place we are halfway done.
We're not going to commit just yet.
We'll wait until we have all the conversion done in the next video.
We're going to finish converting all the other routes.
Stay tuned.
I will see you then.