In the last video you converted two out of the five to do routes to be private in this video we're going
to convert the final three.
The GET BY idea out the delete by id route.
And finally the patch by id route.
Now the process for converting these is going to be really similar to what we did above.
We're going to add yet to Kate middleware.
We're going to update our query to take advantage of the new creator property and finally we'll be updating
the test cases.
We're going to convert the first two routes together the get and delete route.
And your challenge for the video is going to be to convert the third the patch route.
Now before we dive into any of this we are going to need to update these seed data a little bit.
We're going to be adding an authentication token for this second user and that will become clear a little
later as we start updating the test cases.
For now though what I'd like you to do is take the seed data file grab the tokens array and copy it
down below for the second user.
Now we do need to change the ID instead of user one ID.
We're going to pass in a user to ID but with this in place we don't have an authentication token for
both users and we're going to need that in order to fill out the test suite.
Now by making this change we've actually broken some test cases.
We can figure out which ones we've broken and fix them by running NPM test.
It's just a few small changes but it is going to be important to make these changes as well as adding
and betokens array over inside of CDATA.
Yes.
Right here you can see the two tests that are failing are the Post users log in.
Tests should log in a user and return off token fails and should reject invalid loggin fails.
We can head over to the server test file move to the bottom where these test cases live and we'll be
able to make the changes necessary to get everything running right here we have our describe a block
further out post users log in.
In this case we log in with the second user and we make some assertions about the tokens array down
below.
We're asserting that the first item in the tokens array equals the new token we just got back as the
response had it but that's not the case anymore.
It's now going to be the second item in the array.
So I'm going to put one right here inside of brackets as opposed to zero.
This is going to fix this test case.
It will now pass for the test case down below.
We have a similar problem this time around we log in with an invalid password.
We expect to 400 and we expect no token to exist later on we check the tokens right expecting the length
to be zero.
But in reality it should now be one if a token was added the length would be to be logged in invalidly.
So it shouldn't be changed the default length should still exist and the default length goes from 0
to 1 because we've added this item now that we have that in place though we can rerun the test suite
and all of our tests should be passing.
This means that we can finally get started converting those three routes over inside of Adam and we're
going to go into the server js file and we're going to make some changes to this get by id route step
1 of 3 is adding the authenticate middleware.
This is going to make sure our user is logged in and is going to give us access to the user and the
token via the request object.
Next up we're going to need to make a change to our query here we call find by id thatching the to do.
Whose idea was provided in the r.
But this is no longer going to be acceptable.
Currently a user who is logged in could access someone else's to do all that has to do is specify the
ID right here.
They would indeed get logged in even though they don't own that to do.
They wouldn't be able to fetch it and see that data.
We're going to do instead is change fine by ID to find one then instead of just querying by ID we're
going to query by id and by the Creator property right here we're going to make sure underscore ID equals
the ID variable and we're going to make sure creator equals the user's ID the user who's currently logged
in request a user a dot underscore.
I did with this in place we can save the file move into the server test file and scroll up to the appropriate
descry block for that route up near the top of the file.
We're looking for the route for fetching a to do by ID we had that right here and we're going to need
to update these three test cases.
First up I am going to be grabbing the X auth token line from a test case up above since it will be
using that right here for the first one should return a to do dock.
Now the idea we're passing in is the first to Doo's ID and we know that the first to do is owned by
the first user we specify that right here which means over inside of server test.
Yes we can paste the line in as is here.
We provide the token for the first user which is the owner of the to do.
We're trying to fetch which means that we should get a two hundred and our assertion down below should
also pass.
Next up try to return a 404 If no to do.
Found in this case we can go ahead and simply pass in an X off token just like this.
This test case does not require any further changes.
The idea is still not going to exist and we're still going to get a 404 back for the last test.
It's going to go through a similar process.
All we need to do is set X off.
This idea is not going to exist in the database.
It's also not a valid object id which means we will get a 404 back.
Now there is one more test case I want to add.
I want to verify that if I'm logged in as User 1 I can't fetch a to do owned by user 2 I'm going to
go ahead and copy our first test and paste it down below.
Instead of it should return it to do Doc I'm going to say it should not return a to do Doc created by
other user and this time around we're going to try to fetch the second to do item.
We're going to provide the second to do items ID but we're still going to authenticate as the first
user which should cause a problem and we should get a 4.
0 4 back we can remove our custom expect call right here.
We're not going to get any body data back now that we have this in place we can go ahead and rerun our
test suite and make sure all of our test cases are passing.
We should now have all of our tests passing and get around NPM test to start things up.
It's going to go through the entire test suite and if everything is working as expected we can move
on to the delete route.
Right here you can see the four tests for getting it to do by ID are indeed passing.
So now it's time to go back into service dot J S and update the next route the delete route.
This is the last one we're going to do together.
And the process is going to be very similar the same three steps add the middleware update the query
update the test cases.
First up the middle where authenticate and second up is the query.
Currently we use find by id and remove your member from our mongoose remove file.
There's a method called Find one and remove.
This is what we want to use.
We don't just want to find by ID.
We want to find by id and by the Creator which means I'm going to replace by ID with one uppercase.
And now we can add our custom query in here.
We're going to make sure that the underscore ID equals the ID that was provided in the U R L and we're
also going to make sure that the Creator property equals the request.
User ID object id with this in place the delete route has been updated and now we can move into the
test file to update the test cases over inside of server and test Scott.
Yes I'm going to scroll down to the delete route.
Here we have that should remove a to do.
Now for this test we're trying to remove the second to do.
Currently we're not authenticated.
So we're going to do is authenticate as the second user.
That's going to require us to call the set method setting the X auth header.
Now we're going to grab this token from the users array and instead of going to the first user We're
going to go to the second user then we're going to go into their tokens array grab the first token and
pass in the token attribute.
With this in place we're now successfully authenticated as the second to user who does indeed have access
to the second to do.
Which means that everything down below should still work as expected.
The body should still have the ID and it down below when we find that to do we should expect it to not
exist because we deleted it.
I'm also going to add a second to test case really similar to the first one which verifies that if I
try to delete a to do I don't own it doesn't actually get removed I'm going to copy this test case and
down below we can paste it right here.
We're going to start things off by tweaking the to do we try to delete instead of trying to delete that
second to do.
We're going to try to delete the first but we're going to do it as the second user which should cause
an error.
Right here we're going to expect a 4 0 4 back because inside of server J.S. this query this is not going
to return any documents which means this if statement is going to run and the 4:4 will get sent back
back inside of server test.
J.S. we can now go ahead and remove our expectations right here.
Although I am going to keep our custom function down below inside of this function.
We're going to find the to do by id just like we did earlier but instead of expecting it to not exist
we're going to expect it to exist.
The deletion should never have happened because I tried to delete or to do.
I didn't create.
So it should still exist in the database.
The last thing we want to do before we run these two test cases is update the two test cases down below.
Now these can be done with either user.
So all I'm going to do is copy your ex off line right here which provides the second user's token I'm
going to paste it in this test and I'll paste it in the test case below.
With this in place our delete test suite should now be passing over inside of the terminal we can verify
this by rerunning NPM test this time around we should have 21 test cases are 1 Nuwan and everything
should be passing.
Everything looks good so far we're going into the delete section and all of the Delete to do routes
did indeed pass.
This is fantastic.
With this in place the last thing to do is convert the final route the patch route which updates a to
do.
Now in order to get this done you're going to have to go through those same three steps you're going
to add the authentication middleware you're going to update the query and you're going to update the
tests adding the authentication middleware will be the same as it was for every other test case.
But the query is going to be a little different.
Instead of using a find a by idea an update you're going to need to use the other method to find one
and update find a one and update is going to do exactly what you'd expect it's going to return just
one item which is exactly what we want you're also going to need to update the query.
The query is going to be in that first argument.
Currently it's just an idea.
We're going to go ahead and set it equal to an object specifying the underscore id property as well
as the underscore creator property.
Now once you have the server route updated you can go ahead and update the test cases as well down below
under the patch section.
We have one to test cases both of these are going to need to get updated.
And we're also going to add a third right here we have a test.
It should update the.
To do this tries to update the first to do which means we need to authenticate as the first user.
I'll leave a little comment right here off as first user.
Now once you authenticate as that first user everything should work as expected.
You don't need to change any of the assertions down below.
What I'd like you to do then is duplicate the test above duplicate above test and try to update the
first to do as the second user tried to update first to do as second user.
In this case we should get a 404 back and that's exactly what you're going to assert.
Assert 404 response.
Excellent.
Now once you're done that test case you can move on to the final test case.
It should clear completed at when to do is not completed.
In this case we are trying to update the second to do which means you can simply authenticate as the
second user.
You won't need to change anything but adding that X or Hetter all the assertions down below can be exactly
the same.
So take a moment to knock that out.
Feel free to use any of the previous videos or any code you've already written in this project.
You can also use Google and stack overflow if you run into any issues.
This is what real developers use.
I use Google and stack overflow every single day when working on client projects.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock this out rerun the test suite when you're done.
Go ahead and play around with post man.
Make sure everything works as expected.
Then go ahead and click play how to go.
I hope you were able to get all of that done and we're going to kick things off over in the server file.
By modifying the patch route first up step 1 add authenticate middleware authenticate.
Boom done.
Next up update the query instead of find by id and update.
We're going to use find one and update.
This is going to let us provide a custom query where we can specify the two props we've been using for
the other routes.
The underscore ID Propp equal to the ID up above and the underscore creator property set equal to request
dot user dot underscore.
I deal with this in place.
The route is now complete and we can move on to the test case.
I'm going to save the server file.
Move over to the server test file and kick things off by updating the first test.
All we have to do for this one is authenticate as the first user.
I'm going to remove the comment I left as a note.
We can grab the X off token example from up above.
Paste it here and simply change it to the first user instead of the second one done.
That's it for the first test.
We can now move on to the second test which we're going to create by duplicating the first going to
copy it and we'll go ahead and give it a new name.
It should not update that to do created by other user.
Now for this test we wanted to authenticate as the second user.
I'm going to change this from user 0 to users 1 but we wanted to try to update the first to do a to
do that we do not own which means that what we should get back is a 404.
Just like I commented below.
I'm going to remove the expect call and swap out the 200 for the 404 with this in place are second to
test cases done.
We can move on to the other ones down below.
I'm going to grab a call to set adding it to my clipboard and for this test it should clear completed
at when to do is not completed all we need to do is add the author tolk here.
We're trying to update the second to do which means I want to authenticate as the second user.
I'm going to paste in the call.
I already have the second user right here and we are done.
There's nothing left to change all we need to do is save the file and rerun the test suite over inside
of the terminal.
I'm going to rerun the test suite.
We should now have 22 passing tests the previous 21 plus our new test.
Right here we have the delete tests running.
Now we're running our patch tests.
We have three.
They are passing which is fantastic.
And with this in place our users and to do's are associated all of the methods are locked down.
There is no way to update delete Thach or create to do's that you don't own.
You are gonna need to be logged in for all these requests and you're only going to be able to manage
data you have access to.
Let's wrap things up by making a commit to save our changes.
I'm going around get status and we have our changed files everything looks good here.
I can use get commit with the a flag to make a commit associate users with dues.
I'm going to make that commit.
Push it up to get help.
And we are done for this one.
There's two more videos left.
We're going to be looking at how to properly configure our applications pulling stuff like our secrets
out of the code and we're going to apply to her rope you and make sure everything works in the production
version of the application.
That's all coming up next.
So stay tuned.
I will see you then