In this video you're going to learn how to beef up your app configuration.
You're going to look at a better way to store local environment variables and you learn how to set custom
environment variables on Heroku because we have that secret key we use for our JWT tokens that currently
is stored in the code.
We want to break that out to an environment variable for our development and test environments and we
also want to set that as a production environment variable on Heroku.
Now the first thing we're going to do is tweak how we manage our local environment variables.
Currently all of those values are provided inside of config.
J.
And right now this isn't a big problem but it's a really bad idea to have your config variables as part
of your repository.
Now currently we just have a port and a local database you are l which means if someone gets a hold
of this information it's not a big deal but as we start adding secrets and third party API keys you
are going to have valuable information and you do not want that to be added to the get repository.
Now obviously your repo is probably going to be private.
If you have secure information in it but even then it's just one more place.
This data is floating around.
The most important thing to remember as we go through this process is that only development and test
environment variables are configured locally via some file.
The production environment variables those are always going to get configured via either the Heroku
command line tools or the Heroku web application.
Now so far we've only used port and Mongo DB you or I.
Both of those were provided for us by Heroku but we actually have the ability to set any environment
variable we want any key value pair.
We're going to look at how to do that a little bit later.
For now let's focus on getting these environment variables outside of the config file.
Now the config.
JS file is not going to go away completely.
The file is still going to exist and it's actually still going to run on both development test and production
which means we're not going to be changing anything inside of the server.
J.S. file We're still going to load this in regardless of the environment inside of the configfs file
though.
Instead of defining the environment variables for test and development we're simply going to load them
in if we're on the test or development environment.
Now to get this done we are going to add an if statement up above the code below will get removed a
little bit later.
But we are going to keep it around because we still need those values.
If the environment equals development or the environment equals test now Previously we did different
things depending on the environment.
In this case we don't care whether it's test or development.
We just want to run it.
If it's either now inside of here what we're going to do is load in a seperate Jason File.
This is where our development and test configuration variables are going to live and that file config.
Jason.
It is not going to be part of the Get repository.
Now that's going to be a problem on test and development.
If you don't have the file but on production or the file won't exist it's not going to be a problem.
This code is never going to run because the production environment variable will not pass this condition
inside of here.
We are going to be doing some configuration but before we get into that let's go ahead and set up the
Jasen file.
We have the opportunity to set it up however we like.
Whatever makes sense for our application inside of config.
We're going to make a new file called config dot Jason and this file is just going to be a regular Jason
File.
We're going to have key value pairs on the root object where the key is the environment.
Example test and the value is an object.
We're going to have one more test and we're going to have one for development now inside of these objects
for development and test.
We can specify any local environment variables.
For example inside of the local test environment we have two variables.
We have port and Mongo DVH.
I am going to set port inside of double quotes equal to the value 3000 and I can also set Mongo DB.
You or I equal to whatever value I had previously.
Now this is Jason's of the value which is a string is going to need to be wrapped in double quotes.
I'm going to grab it from the config file and paste it into the adjacent file right inside of the quotes.
Now this configures all of our test environment variables but we do still have some development ones
we want to grab.
We have port which is identical port get set to 3000.
We also have Mongo DB you are-I and that is going to get set equal to a string and we're going to grab
the value we used previously this can get copied and pasted right into the config.
Jason File and we are done.
Now that we've moved all the variables over to the new Jason File we can wipe our old if statement.
I'm not going to delete it.
I'm just going to comment it out so it doesn't actually run when we eventually run the program.
Now the next thing we need to do is figure out how to get these values we need access to this object
so we can properly set up process.
EMV right here for example we set process.
Ian VDM port equal to 3000.
We need a system to do the exact same thing but it needs to use this Jasen file.
Now the first thing we're going to do which is a great great feature is required the Jason File.
And when you require Jason it actually automatically parses it into a javascript object.
We don't have to use anything like Jason and parse it to get that done.
This means we can make a variable called config and we can set it equal to the return result from require.
And we're going to require a local file so we'll start with that forward slash.
It's in the current directory so we can simply name it config dot Jason and adding the extension here
because that is important.
Now what we have access to is this config object.
I'm going to go ahead and log it to the screen so we can see exactly what it looks like.
Console that log config and we can save the file running config.
J.S. from the terminal.
Now normally we wouldn't be doing this but we can do it in this case.
I'm going to run the file in the folder server then it's in the folder config file itself is called
config.
Yes.
When we run it what do we get back.
We get back our object with the test property that has port and Mongo DB you or I and we have our development
property with the same two environment variables set up.
This means we have our object.
Now we just need to figure out how to use that object to set the process NVI object.
The first thing we want to do is grab just the environment variables for the environment we're currently
in.
If Ian V is equal to development all we want is this object if it's equal to test all we want is the
test variables right here.
I'm going to create a separate variable called var V config.
This is going to store just the config variables for the current environment and I'm going to set this
equal to the config object and we're going to use bracket notation to grab the environment.
I'm going to pass in the environment variable.
So if Ian V is equal to test we're gonna grab the test property.
If Ian B is equal to development we're going to grab that development property when you want to use
a variable to access a property you have to use bracket notation like this.
Now that we have the Ian V config variable all we need to do is a loop over it.
And for each property for example port we want to set that on process.
Ian V We want to do it for everything inside of the object which in this case is just two.
Now the first two we're going to use to get that done is something called object ADOT keys object keys
takes an object like NVI config.
It gets all of the keys and it returns them as an array.
We can go ahead and log this to the screen to see exactly what we get.
I'm going to wrap it in parentheses.
Call console dialog.
Save the file and rerun it from the terminal.
When I rerun the file from the terminal what we see is an array where we have the port environment variable
in upper case and mango D-B you are I now that we have this all we need to do is loop over the array
doing something for each item.
I'm going to remove the council that lag call and we're going to call for each which as we know lets
us loop over an array of items.
It takes a callback function as it's one and only argument and that callback function gets called with
each item.
I'm going to call each item the key.
This means that we're going to have a function which we'll get called with a key of port and a key of
Mongo DB.
You are I inside of here.
We can then set process that EMV dot using bracket notation key.
If the key is Port we're selling the port property on NV.
If the key is Mongo db that you or I were setting the Mongo DB You are property on NV and we're going
to set that equal to whatever the value is in EMV config.
D-NV config and we're going to grab the value for the key just like this.
And with this in place we are done.
We don't have a much better system for managing that local configuration.
I'm going to go ahead and remove the commented code.
Save the file.
And before we do anything else we want to ignore the configuration file via GET ignore inside of here.
Currently we just ignore node modules.
We're going to add a second line ignoring a file.
The file is in the server directory.
Then we're going to go into the config directory and the file itself is called config dot Jason.
With this in place the configuration file will never get added to the repository.
Over in the terminal if I run get status you can see the new file is nowhere in sight.
We have our two modified changes showing up but we do not have that configuration file because it has
been successfully ignored from the local repository.
Now this was step one coming up with a system to manage local environment variables.
This also lets us easily add a new environment variable.
Right here we're going to add one called JWT secret.
If you remember inside of the test seed file we reference ABC 1 2 3 2 times when we call it JWT dot
sign.
This is a pretty big problem and the problem also exists inside of our model user file.
Down here we have a few calls to JWT sign and a call to JWT verify.
Both of these have the exact same string inside of them but we need to do is instead of having the string
inside of the code we need to pull that out into an environment variable and reference the environment
variable right here and over in the seed file.
Now the first step to that is going to be to create the environment variable.
Let's go ahead and make one called uppercase JWT underscore secret and we're going to set this equal
to whatever secret string we want to use.
I recommend using something long and random.
You do not need to use the same value.
I'm going to go ahead and just press on the keyboard a little bit.
Coming up with a nice set of numbers and letters.
I don't need to actually remember this value because it's stored as a config variable.
I'm going to also do the same thing for development right here.
I'm going to set JWT secret equal to whatever I like and I'm gonna come up with a new and unique string.
Something slightly different but pretty similar in terms of its randomness.
Now that we have this in place we have a JWT secret variable we can access in both the test and development
varments which means we can update the code inside of seed.
J.S..
End user dot.
J.S. Right here.
Instead of having our secret write in the code we will reference process and V dot J W T underscore
secret and we're going to do the exact same thing down below.
I'm going to copy this statement paste it right here and we can do the same thing over inside of user
datcha.
Yes I'm going to save and close the seed file inside of user.
We're going to do it for JWT sign call and we're also going to do it down below for the JWT varify call
which uses the same exact secret to verify a token was indeed created by who it says it was.
Now that we have our user file updated we can save it and close it to make sure everything still works
as expected with this new configuration.
Over inside of the terminal I'm going to run NPM test and make sure all my test cases still pass and
everything should still pass.
We have our environment variables in place they're in place for the test environment.
So as far as the tests are concerned nothing should have changed.
All we've done is changed how the environment variables get set.
Over here you can see we have 22 passing tests which is fantastic.
We can also run a quick development test by starting up the app using node server server J.S. and running
a few calls from postman for example over inside a post.
Man I could create a new user using the post user's request.
I'm going to make a new user with the email.
Andrew 9 at example dot com.
If I send that off I get a 200.
I get my X off hetter back I can grab that had a value and tried to do something like fetch my dues.
I'm going to go ahead and fetch my dues.
There shouldn't be any because I haven't created any.
Remember this is a private call so we're going to add an X header.
We're going to paste in the value we send it off we get no tattoos but that's fine.
We don't have any.
As long as the call was successfully authenticated then we can be pretty sure all of our environment
variables were configured properly.
Now that we have our local configuration in place it's time to talk about how we're going to configure
the JWT secret variable for production locally we just specify it here but when we want to configure
on Heroku we have to do something slightly different over inside of the terminal.
We're going to take a look at a series of Heroku commands to get the job done.
Let's go ahead and clear the terminal output and the first command we're going to run Heroku config
is something we've already executed.
We ran this previously to get the value of Mongo DB you or I here's my value.
This should be the only one that shows up.
Now we know there is a poor environment variable configured somewhere in the app that has a Heroku specific
environment variable.
You're not going to be able to update that value so it's not visible here.
Now we have one environment variable showing up a key value pair.
We can go ahead and actually set our own to do this.
We're going to run Heroku space config Colan set.
This takes a key value pair.
The key could be something like name and the value which comes after the equal sign could be whatever
you like.
Go ahead and set your name right here.
I'm going to set Andrew then I'm going to hit enter.
Now as you can see it's setting and restarting the application.
This means that it's going to restart the app so the app has access to the new environment variable
and we can run Heroku config again and this time around we should see our environment variable.
And we do.
Sitting right here we have name and it's set equal to Andrew.
Now aside from viewing and setting variables we can also go ahead and get an individual environment
variables value Heroku config dot get lets us do that.
All we do is specify the name of the environment variable to fetch.
In this case I could specify name and right here and you can see Andrew returns the last command we
can use to manage these environment variables is Heroku config colon on set unset removes an environment
variable.
Now we never want to unset Mongo DB You are right.
But in this case we could onsets name we use Heroku config on set followed by the uppercase name environment
variable.
We run it this onsets it and restarts the app.
And if we run Heroku config for a final time you can see we're right back where we started.
Now that we know how to set these environment variables we need to do is set one called JWT secret.
We're setting this to make sure our calls to JWT seinen JWT varify don't fail on production.
Currently they would because the environment variable would not be defined.
Go ahead and take a quick moment to set a JWT underscore environment variable setted equal to some random
string.
Then go ahead and fetch it.
Making sure it was set properly when you're done.
You can go ahead and click play.
All right.
Not one should have been pretty easy.
All you had to do was run Heroku config Kolins set to set the environment variable.
We're going to create one called JWT underscore secret.
The exact same name as the local environment variable and as the environment variable we referenced
in our files.
It's really important that all of these line up.
Otherwise the program is not going to work as expected.
Now back inside of the terminal we can go ahead and set this equal to using the equal sign.
Some sort of random string you can go ahead and jam the keyboard for a little bit.
Coming up with something good.
Then we can go ahead and run the command right here you can see it setting JWT secret and it's restarting
the application.
If I run Heroku config we are going to see our environment variable showing up which is fantastic if
you're seeing this here with the value you set.
Then you are done with all of our config code properly working we can go ahead and make a commit.
I'm going to run get status.
Here we see we have our For changed files which is expected.
I can then run get commit with the a m flag to leave a commit message a good message for this one is
update config to use Jason File.
I'm also going to push this up to get and this is where will stop for this one in the next video which
is the final video for the section we're going to go ahead and get the app running on Heroku once again.
Stay tuned.
I will see you soon.