In this video we're going to get the to do API back on Heroku before we do though.
Let's go ahead and connect to our production database via robo Mongo so we can manage that data.
We have some really old leftover data from before we updated the to do end user models.
Now to get that you are Al we know we can run a command from the terminal Heroku config would work.
Or more specifically we can run Heroku config call and get followed by the environment variable name
Mongo D-B underscore you are I and what we get back is a really long connection string.
Now this connection string actually contains a ton of really useful information.
We're going to need to know which piece is which because we're going to have to add all of this into
individual fields inside of the Roble Mongo application in Roboam Mongo.
If we go ahead and add a new connection by clicking the two computers and clicking create you see that
we don't get a place for a long connection sharing.
Instead we have things like address port and under authentication we have things like database username
and password.
All of this exists inside of the string we have right here.
Now the first part the part I have highlighted this is the protocol.
It's a mongo DB connection request.
Next up we have the username and password.
This starts after the protocol and it goes up to the at symbol right in the middle somewhere you should
see a call on everything before the colon.
What I have highlighted here is the user name.
Everything between the colon and the at symbol.
That is the password.
Now after that we have the address itself after the address.
We have the port and after the Port we have a forward slash followed by the database we're going to
go ahead and transfer all of this information into Roboam Mongo.
Starting with the actual address.
Everything from at to the Kallen.
I'm going to copy this to the clipboard.
Move over into Roboam Mongo and paste it right in the address field under connection.
I can also give this connection a name Heroku to do API.
Next up let's go ahead and grab the port the port which we can get over inside of the terminal is 1
7 7 3 6.
I'm going to copy that move into robo Mongo and paste it right here.
Next up under authentication we're going to have to perform authentication providing a database a user
name and a password.
We can keep the off mechanism the default value as shown here.
First up the database the database is the very end of the connection string after the forward slash.
We have our database name.
We can simply copy this take it and paste it into the database field.
Next up username and password.
Let's do the user name first.
Over inside of the terminal we have our user name right here and you'll notice the user name is actually
identical to the database name.
I'm going to go ahead and copy it anyways in case yours is not.
So it should be and over inside of Roboam Mongo we can paste it inside of the user name field.
The last field to copy is the password that exists over inside of the connection string between the
colon and the at symbol.
I'm going to copy this pasted inside of Roboam mango and before we click Save go ahead and click the
test button the test button is going to test the connection before you actually save the details.
So if something goes wrong you can change it without having to edit the existing connection.
Right here we have a couple checkmarks it looks like everything did go as expected.
I can close the test save that connection and then we can connect it to the database by double clicking
it.
Now over in the left hand side we have our local Mongo database and we have our Heroku to do API database.
I can open up the individual database go into collections and inside of here we have a dues collection.
This has some really old data.
So I'm going to go ahead and drop this now.
We have our database with no collections and no documents.
This means that we are good to go.
We can deploy to Heroku and everything should work as expected.
Now things are only going to work as expected because we have all our environment variables configured
including the database you are l n d j.
W T.
Secret.
If you do not have the JWT secret configured from the last video this call is not going to work as expected.
Make sure to have a value right here just like we set up previously.
With this in place though I can run get status to confirm I have no changes that need to be committed
and I can run get push Heroku master to deploy to Heroku.
This is going to take about 15 seconds after it actually finishes it'll take about another 15 seconds
to get the service started but once it's up and running we can play around with it inside of post man
making sure everything works as expected.
Right here we are verifying the deploy.
Everything looks like it went well and we're back at the terminal.
Let's go ahead and test things out.
Over inside of postmen.
Now over inside of postman we need to switch from to do app local to do app Heroku But once we do we
can make any of the requests we previously set up.
I'm going to get started by creating a user.
We can make the user with the default data since no users exist.
I can send this off and down below we get a 200 and we can see the user was indeed created.
We also get our X auth headers sitting right here.
I can go ahead and grab this added to my clipboard and we can make some secure requests.
For example getting the user who's currently logged in I'm going to go ahead and provide the header
value as the X auth header send off the request and in the response body what do we get back we get
back the ID and the email as expected.
Now let's go ahead and manage some to do's using the production API.
We're going to set the X off Hetter equal to the value of the token.
I have some body data already set up so I can go ahead and send off this one.
And down below we have our to do item.
I'm going to make a second one as well.
Eat some food.
Not that I need to remind myself to do this.
I can send that off and now we have to do's inside of the database.
I'm going to make a get to do is call next to confirm that I need to do's were indeed added to the database
at the South Hetter.
Send this one off and down below we get our call back.
We have a 200 status code which is great and we have the two to do items we just created.
From here we can go ahead and play around with a few other routes.
I'm going to take this first to do and I'm going to try to update it using patch.
I can go into patch I can update the body setting completed to true and setting the text equal to nothing.
I'm not going to update the text then I can update the ID inside of the you R-AL and I can grab the
X header value from one of the previous requests headers X off I'm going to grab that old value move
into the patch call and add it right here.
There we go.
Now we're updating one of the to do is we just created were properly logged in and all we're doing is
toggling it from false to true.
If I send this off down below we get back the new to do we see that completed is equal to true.
And we now have a completed at time stamp as well which is fantastic.
Last up let's tried to delete the to do item and make sure that works also.
I'm going to go ahead and grab the ID.
Open up the Delete to do call paste the ID right in here then we can go ahead and grab the X off Hetter
from one of the previous requests.
I'm going to paste that into the headers Section X hyphen off putting it right here.
We can send this one and we get a 200 back with our to do that to do that just got removed.
If we now go back to the old get to do is request and rerun it down below we should see we just have
1 to do item in place.
Last up let's log out.
I'm going to grab the south Hetter we've been using all along.
Head to the delete users me token call pass in the proper token value send that off and we get a 200.
Now if we try to make any of the previous calls like get to do's we're going to get a 401.
Unauthorized and that is because we have logged out destroying that token.
Now all of this was also updated inside of robo Mongo.
If I refreshed that connection and open up the collections list you can now see we have the two dues
collection and the users collection and inside of there we have all the appropriate data.
We have our user sitting right here and the password is successfully hashed using the crypt and inside
of the to do's collection.
We have our document with our one to do item now though we have this in place.
We are done with the to do application.
I hope you had a good time setting up this API learning how to create and test end points setting up
mongoose and Mongo D-B managing configuration using POST man and Roboam mango until it was a lot in
the last two sections.
But this is one of the most real world node app examples I've created applications so similar to this
for clients.
Obviously it wasn't meant to do API.
It was to manage something else.
But the techniques are identical.
I used the exact same tool sets when creating those apps including Heroku for deploying my applications.
Now we are done but I am going to run into the terminal and for sanity's sake run get status one more
time just to make sure no files were changed.
We can see none were.
So that is it.
That's it for this section it's also it for the to do API.
Once again thanks for joining me I will see you in the next section.
Stay tuned.