In this video you are going to learn some advanced post-match techniques.
Now if you're anything like me that last video probably drove you mad.
We were copying around x values and to do IDs.
It's a real cumbersome process.
There is a better way to do things.
But we're going to do instead is use environment variables when we issue sign up or log in requests.
We're going to grab that X off Hetter and set it equal to an environment variable.
So instead of having to update every x auth header for every request we can simply provide the environment
variable and it's automatically going to get updated as we log in with a new account.
The South environment variable will get updated and we can use it in any of the other requests.
Now in order to get that done and explain exactly how it's going to work I am going to close all of
my tabs not saving any of them.
And we're going to get started by updating the sign up call.
Now the sign of call is going to get an x auth token back.
This is going to come back like it has for all of our other requests.
I'm going to create a user Andrew 10 out example dot com.
Right here we get our head back and this is what we want to set as the value for the environment variable
and postman.
It gives us a way to do that to do that we're going to go into this tests section the tests section
is a little place where we can run some code after a request comes back.
You could use this to verify that the request worked as expected.
In our case we have a test suite that does that for us.
Instead we're going to use this little test text area to manage some environment variables.
Now on the right hand side postman has a fantastic set of snippets to get you started.
What we're going to do is write two lines.
We're going to write two lines that one fetch the token and to set the token equal to an environment
variable.
Now currently our to do app Heroku environment has one environment variable depending on the version
of Postman you can do that by either going here and clicking manage environments or in my case simply
clicking this little preview icon.
One of these three things should be the location for your version of postman right here I have the you
are an environment variable.
What we're going to do is add an X off environment variable.
Now first up we're going to make a variable called token setting and equal to the response hador we
can get that using POST man and post man which is an object has a bunch of awesome utility methods we
can use to manipulate things inside of our tests text area.
We're going to use the get response Hetter method get response Haueter takes the name of the header
whose value you want to fetch.
We're going to fetch the X off Hetter value and then we're going to go ahead and set the environment
variable.
Using postman datt set environment
variable passing into arguments the first one is the name of the environment variable to set.
I'm going to call mine x off which matches up with the header name and the second is the value you want
to set.
We have that stored under the token variable.
And with this in place we are done we can now save this request and issue it off by creating a new user.
I'm going to change 10 to 11.
Send this off and when we send it things look pretty similar.
We still get our XT off token in the headers and our body still looks correct with a 200 status.
The difference now is that inside of our environment we have an X off environment variable.
This is the token that just came back which means we can use this elsewhere in our code to make the
private requests a lot easier to send off for example get to deuce get to deuce currently fails.
It is going to require an X header.
Previously we had to copy that value every time.
Instead we can simply reference the environment variable opening and closing two sets of curly braces
and putting the environment variable name right inside.
Now we can issue this request without ever needing to actually copy of value which means we don't need
to change the request every time we just click it clicked send and we get the data back.
Now this is fantastic.
We have this saved to save it again.
Updating the abody.
Now we can go ahead and copy the exact same two lines to the logon request.
Remember both sign up and log in they are both open and get an x auth token back.
I'm going to save this one send it off and now we have a new X off value already in the environment.
This is the new token value that just came back with this in place.
We can now update all of our private requests just like we did to get to dues.
Right here we set X off equal to x off we're going to do the same thing for post to do.
X hyphen auth is going to equal the X auth environment variable.
Then we can save this one.
We can move on to get to do by id setting X hyphen off equal to the X auth environment variable.
We have the same thing for delete to Doo's down below X auth equals the X environment variable and we're
going to keep moving down the list.
Patch is up next x off and X off next up after that one is the get users me.
This one already has the X header defined I just need to update the value.
And finally we have our alag out request right here.
We're going to swap out the token value with the X off environment variable.
Now we will never need to do that again.
Any time we want to make a private request all we do is we click the route we send it off and we get
the data back.
Now this works great with X auth.
I also want to do the exact same thing for the to do de-value we've been passing around.
Ideally the default value would just be the last to do created and we can add that functionality by
changing the post to Doo's route.
Right.
Here we have our tests section and what we're going to do is grab the ID from the response body and
we're going to set that equal to an environment variable just like we did with X off then we'll be able
to use that environment variable inside of the U R L right here inside of post to do what we're going
to do first is grab the body by creating a variable called Body and we are going to need to call Jason
dot parce to take the adjacent value and convert it into a javascript object.
Now postman is going to give you access to the Jasen response via response body.
Excellent.
Now that we have our body object we can go ahead and call set environment variable.
Once again postman daat set environment variable passing in our values.
A good name for this one would be to do ID and we're going to set it equal to body dot underscore ID
which is where that property is located.
Now I can go ahead and save this request and we can fire it off.
Take a moment to notice that you do not have to do Id environment variable.
When you send it off and you go back to the same screen you now do have to do id variable.
It's the exact same ID we have right here.
It ends in 4:6 down below and it ends in 4:6 right there.
Now we can go ahead and update the to do routes that require an ID by simply taking the ID portion of
the U R L and swapping it out for the environment variable to do Id just like this for our get to dues
by ID request.
I'm going to save it and send it off and right here we get that to do we just created we can also do
the same thing for patch.
I'm going to update Doley last right here.
We're going to swap out the ID with to do Id say that send it off and now we have it to do it where
the status is completed and the completed at property has a time stamp.
Last up is the delete route.
I'm going to swap out the ID with the to do Id environment variable.
Save it and send it off.
Now the to do has been deleted and we could still issue our other requests but they're not going to
work as expected.
Here we try to get a to do that was deleted so we get a 4 or 4 but that's fine.
We now have a much easier system for managing our requests.
And the same thing is going to work locally automatically.
I'm going to switch from to do app Heroku to to do app local.
I am going to need to start up my server over in the terminal node server forward slash server genius's
going to get that server up and running.
And inside of a robo Mongo.
I'm going to go ahead and wipe the local collections in here we have our to do our database.
I can simply drop it.
And then we can go into postman and fire off a few requests over inside a post man we'll get started
by creating a user.
I'm going to create a user and automatically everything is already working as expected.
We have our X auth headers sitting right here and we don't need to copy the value from the response
header.
We can move right to get to Doo's issue that request and we can see we have no to do's that's fine let's
go ahead and create one by clicking it and clicking send.
Now we have to do.
And now the to do id is also populated from here we can go ahead and get the individual to do returning
need to do.
Based on the environment variable we could update it just like we did for Heroku.
We can delete it just like we did for Heroku and we can also manage the user.
We can get the user based off of the X auth token and finally to wrap things up we can go ahead and
log out the user.
Now the private requests are going to fail because the token that's provided the one that's still in
the environment variable has been wiped from the database.
So we're going to get a 401.
On authorized.
Now we did the same thing for loggin loggin is also going to set an X auth token which means if we loggin
with a proper body the current body is Andrew an example dotcom but the user I created was Andrew 11.
I'm going to go ahead and log in as our new 11.
Saving the route now the X out token is properly updated.
We can make a request like this and it works as expected with this in place we are done.
We have a much better system for managing our routes inside of postman instead of needing to copy around
to do Id values and X or tokens.
We can simply use environment variables to get the job done.
I highly recommend configuring this sort of setup for any API you're going to create down the line.
It takes just a few minutes to set up initially but it makes life so much easier when it comes to testing
and issuing all of the requests you have saved in your collections.
That is it for the bonus video I will see you in the next section.