And you're here with an expect upgrade guide as promised this bonus video is going to show you how to
upgrade from expect a version one to expect a version at twenty one.
Now there were not 19 other versions in between.
Expect it changed owners.
So it went from a V-1 version right to a 20 version and now we are at v 21.
So that's the one that we're going to be using in this video.
I'm going to show you how to upgrade the entire test suite to the new version of expect at the end all
of our test cases will still be passing but using this brand new version.
Now before we dive into the code at all I do want to make you aware of where you can find the new documentation.
Now the API eyes are so similar.
We're really only going to need to change a few of our expect calls quite a few of them are not going
to change at all.
So I'm going to switch over to the browser and we're going to head over to the M. Jackson expect documentation.
This is the documentation we've already been using and we're going to pull up in another tab the just
expect documentation.
So just is another testing framework like Moka though just is mostly geared towards people who are doing
client side testing things like react.
J.S. for example we're not going to be switching to geste.
We are just going to be using the expect package which happens to be documented on this site.
So when we head over here we can see we have access to an API that should look pretty familiar.
If I scroll down to one of the first examples you can see we call expect we pass something in and we
make an assertion about it.
So a lot of our existing assertions including ones using to be are not going to change at all.
There are just a few name changes and that's really it.
We do not need to change a ton of code.
We just have to change a few things to get things working.
Now the old documentation does show this as part of the documentation they show you that the ownership
has switched it's been donated to just so all future documentation will be over there and that's exactly
where we are right now.
So this is the docs that you would use going forward if you are going to upgrade to the twenty one.
The first thing we are going to do is upgrade to the latest version.
So if I do go ahead and google NPM expect that's going to bring us over to the package page.
And once we are there we'll be able to see that version 21 is the latest version and this is exactly
what we're going to be using the twenty one point one point zero.
So let's go ahead and actually get that installed.
I'm going to switch over to the terminal.
Now I do have mango D-B running in the background in this first tab.
I'm going to run the installation command to get that version set up right here.
That would be NPM install expect at the version that we just looked at.
That is v 20 1.1 point zero.
Twenty one point one.
Point zero.
And I will use the save dev flag to make sure to save the new version as a development dependency.
Now once we run this it's going to go through the process of actually installing the new code in our
project.
And if we switch over to Adam to take a look at exactly what changed we can see that right now under
Debb dependencies we are viewing the new version as opposed to the one.
Now with this in place we can go ahead and just run the test suite something that would have worked
before we ran this command with NPM test and we are going to see quite a few failures.
We're going to see failures related to us using expect methods that do not exist.
Right here you can see we have seven failures for example we have to not exist is not a function to
exist is not a function.
We have the same two again.
Right here we have to be a.
So we see there are about three.
In reality there are a few more that are hidden methods that we're going to need to make changes to.
So all we have to do essentially is rename these to the compatible method from the new version of expect.
So let's go ahead and dive into our code.
We're going to be working with the server test file where all of our test cases live.
It's important to remember that the expect a library is only responsible for these calls when we actually
use the global expect variable if we're using the expect method that is coming from super test and we
do not need to make any tweaks to those.
So right here for example we have our very first one we expect the body text to be the variable tax
death or the same great.
If not we have a problem.
And this is one of the test cases that does not need to change if we head over to the documentation
for the new expect version.
We can scroll down through the methods we can see that we do have to be it should be sitting down here
somewhere.
It looks like it is right here and it to be is described exactly as it was in V-1.
We take two things and we compare them using strict equality.
So we need to make any changes to that particular assertion.
All instances of that one can stay in place if we continue to scroll down.
We have a couple of more newbies those don't need to change.
If we move on to the test cases we have quite a few to BS.
So we're doing pretty well so far right here just to BS all the way down.
Once again no actual expect calls.
Just using super test.
We're going to continue moving down looking for that first one and it's actually going to come right
here when we start describing how the delete method works down below.
Well we do used to be.
We also use to not exist and this is one of the ones we saw that no longer exists ironically to not
exist has been renamed.
So when we're using jast we're not going to have access to to not exist or to exist.
Instead over inside of the expect documentation if I scroll up to the top we're going to be using to
be falsie or to be Sruthi where to be falsie is the equivalent of to not exist and to be truthy is the
equivalent of to exist.
So that means over inside of our code we have to do is swap out to not exist for it to be falsie to
be fallacy is going to throw an error if the thing passed in is not falce in which case we have a problem
if it is falce something like Knol undefined then we're going to go and then is going to work with this
particular test case.
So this test case is actually all cleaned up and if we save the server test file I should be able to
rerun the test suite from the terminal and we should see less than seven failing test cases.
Once again we're moving through the entire test suite.
We do still have some failures this time around though you can see it is just six test cases.
So let's keep on moving down the list.
If we scroll down to the very next test case we can see we do use to exist which no longer exists for
this one we want to use to be truthy and this is going to allow us to make the correct assertion I'm
going to scroll down to the next test case in here we don't use expect at all.
Same with the one down below that then we come up to our patch related test cases and in the very first
one we do have a few assertions using expect we use to be twice.
And those are fine.
But we also use to be a to be a no longer exists.
And there really is no equivalent in terms of making an assertion using the new version of expect.
So to fix this we're just going to use the type of operator a core javascript feature to get the type
for value.
And then we'll just use to be to assert something about it.
I'm going to comment out this particular test case and below if you don't remember we just use type
of.
Followed by something.
So it could be the string Andrew or a variable whose value is a string and the result would be string.
If I did type of true for example the result of that one would be the string boolean.
So we're going to be able to get that type back as a string for anything in this case we are hoping
the type of is a number.
So right here we are going to use expect and we're still going to expect something about completed at
we're just going to use the type of operator up front.
So we're going to get the type of it completed and then we'll make an assertion about that type of response.
Dot a body dot to do dot completed at.
If that type of is a number.
Great.
So we're going to use to be number to make that assertion.
If it's not a number then we have a problem this assertion will fail and the test case will fail.
So with this one in place we are all done and now I am going to go ahead and rerun the test suite to
at least make sure we are making a little bit of progress.
Last time we ran it we had six failing test cases this time around we should have about four.
But here we do indeed have four which means we are ready to continue on migrating away from expect V-1
and towards expect v. 21.
I'm going to keep moving down the list in the next test case we don't seem to use any custom assertions
down below that one.
We do have some custom assertions.
We have to be twice.
And we also have to not exist remember to not exist no longer exists.
The equivalent would be to be falsie.
Now that test case is all cleaned up and we can keep moving down the list.
The next guy has a couple of assertions using to be no need for a change there.
After that one we just have two equal and two equal is also the same.
So remember to be users triple equals to compare two things.
This does not work with objects two equal uses an algorithm to check all of the properties.
This does work with objects and it also exists in the new version of expect.
So you don't need to change any of our two equal calls down below if we can continue on down.
We do have a test case with quite a few assertions.
We start off with it to exist twice remember that no longer exists.
The equivalent is to be truthy.
We're going to use that here and we're also going to use it down below for the other one.
And the third one is 2B which does not need to change.
Down below we have a couple of more in this test case we have to exist once again which doesn't exist
to be truth as we used above.
And then we have to not be there actually is no equivalent for to not be in expect 21.
So let's head over to the documentation and see what we can do about that.
So we're going to be using instead is right here in dot not dot not lets us reverse and assertion so
here they're expecting the return value from this function to not be the string coconut.
If it's anything but coconut great if it is coconut.
This test case will fail and we're going to use the exact same thing inside of our code.
So if I switch over to Adam all we're going to do is switch this assertion to to B.
This is the opposite of what we want.
We're going to toss dot not up front.
And now we have the correct assertion making sure that user dot password is not equal to the password
variable and that should be it for this test case.
I'm going to go ahead and save this one and continue down through the test cases in the next one.
We do not use expect anywhere the same for the test case after it.
Down here we do use expect we have to exist right here.
Instead we will use to be truthy.
Double-O we have a nother assertion and this is going to be one of the last tricky ones to include not
in the expected 21 library but there is another way to get that done and we're going to look at that
right now.
So to include not going to work for our purposes let's head over to the Jeste docs and we're going to
go way up to the top where we have the Table of Contents.
Now if we scroll down the one that we're going to be looking for is to match object to match object
expects that one object contains all of the properties from another.
So here they're expecting something about the house for sale object and they're expecting it to match
the object desired house.
Now the properties aren't exactly the same but desired house is a subset of house for sale.
It has everything up above except for bedrooms which is missing.
And we also do not have the kitchen area property but that's OK.
We're not expecting them to be equal.
We're just expecting that this object contains all of the things outlined here.
And that's exactly the sort of thing we're trying to do with our test case.
Now there is one small quirk to this the old expect or version one was able to correctly parse out all
of the stuff from mongoose that is on user.
The new version is going to throw an error.
So all we're going to do is use two object and two object is just going to return the raw user data
with none of the internal methods or inner workings of mongoose present.
This is just going to be the user object as we see it inside of the database now we're still going to
be accessing the tokens array and we're still going to grab the second one instead of to include.
We will be using to match object.
And there we go.
That is all we need to do for this one.
So anytime we are trying to work with objects we can still get this sort of assertion done.
We're just going to be using the new method.
I'm going to switch back over to the terminal and I will rerun the test suite once again and see what
sort of progress we've made.
If my memory serves we should have just one failing test left to take care of.
And it looks like I was correct.
Right here we have one test case to not exist is being used.
So we're going to have to go ahead and tweak that.
Let's continue moving through the test case as it's actually sitting right here to not exist should
be to be falsie.
So as you can see the process of upgrading from expect one to expect 21 really isn't that bad.
At its core they're both the exact same thing.
They aim to solve the same problems and they solve them in very similar ways.
We're really just talking about a difference in naming.
So we have to switch the names around a little bit which can be annoying but now with just those few
changes you are ready to continue using the latest version of expect throughout your node development
career.
We now have a completely passing test case and we're ready to continue on to the next section.
Feel free to commit and deploy as you see fit.
I'm not going to go through that process here since we have gone through that process plenty of times
before.
That is it for this bonus upgrade.
Video Let's go ahead and dive back in to the regularly scheduled programming.