In this video to headed down the path towards authentication we're going to be adding the necessary
properties to the user model that are currently missing.
Currently the user document has only one property an email and the email isn't even validated.
We have to make some changes to this one as well as adding a few new ones.
Now to show you exactly what a user document is going to look like when we're all done I'm going to
make a simple object right here.
This is going to be what the doc looks like but you do not need to write this code.
I'll be deleting it in just a moment.
First up obviously we're going to have that email property.
It is going to be validated which means we will require it to look like a real valid e-mail Andrew at
example dot com would pass the validation.
Next up for signing up and logging in we are going to need a password from the user.
So it will set up a password property and the user will send in their password in plain text.
If they type my pass one to three my pass one to three is going to come to the server.
We're not going to store it in plain text though because that is not secure.
If the database gets compromised the person who hacked the database will not have access to the person's
e-mail and their plain text password which is a really big problem.
Not only could they log into our service but a lot of people use the same password across other services.
So they might be able to log in to someone's bank account or other accounts you obviously don't want
someone hacking into.
This means that we're going to be hashing this password and using the secret algorithm which we'll talk
about later.
Essentially a one way hash means we take this value and we convert it into a really long string of a
fixed length regardless of the value passed in.
And this is what we're going to store in the database.
It's impossible to get the original value back from the hash value.
It is a one way algorithm meaning we can take a value and hash it but we can't on hash value.
That's exactly what we want to hear.
We never want to be storing our passwords in plain text.
Now the last property we're going to be adding is called tokens tokens is actually going to be an array.
It's going to be an array of objects where each object is a log in token.
Imagine I log in that to do application for my mobile phone and the Web site I'm going to want to have
different authentication tokens.
And those are going to get stored in the tokens array.
Now an individual token is going to look something like this will have an access property that specifies
the token type.
The only one will be setting up in this course is an authentication token type although you could have
other tokens for verifying things like email or resetting passwords.
Next up we're going to have the actual token value.
This will be stored under the token property.
And this is also like the password going to be a really strong cryptographically secure string.
This is the string that we're going to pass back and forth when a user wants to make a secure request.
They're going to send this along with their request and we'll be able to validate that the user does
indeed have access to do what they want to do whether it's deleting a to do adding a to do or updating
to do.
Now this is that user model we want to create.
So let's go ahead and do it down below.
First up the e-mail there's a few things we need to change there.
The first property we're going to add is a property called unique the unique property which gets set
to either true or false.
We'll be setting it to true in this case verifies that the property e-mail does not have the same value
as any other documents in the collection.
And now John I'm signing up for a new account with an e-mail that's already in use it would pass if
I had unique set to false which is the default value.
But when we set Unique equal to true we won't be able to have two documents in use or collection with
the same e-mail and this is a good thing.
Next up we're going to add custom e-mail validation we need to verify that the string that got passed
in is a valid email.
Validating emails is an inherently tricky thing to do.
There are a ton of edge cases and work arounds that need to be in place in order for e-mail validation
to work in all cases rather than writing and testing this library on our own.
We're going to use a validator library that has and is email function.
It's a really simple function it is well tested and well used which means that we can guarantee it's
going to work for our purposes.
Now to set up customer validation we're going to take a quick look at the docs.
So you know where it exists because there are a few features that we won't be using here but that are
really useful to get to the docs page.
We're going to google mongoose in lower case there's no need to scream at the browser.
Custom validation.
The first result should be what we want mongoose validation.
It starts off with the basic validation that you already know how to do this.
But down below there is a custom validators section.
Here we have a phone attribute and on the attribute object along with the type we have that validate
validate takes two properties the validate or this is the actual function that makes sure the value
is valid and the message inside of the message we can even inject the actual value used.
So we can say that ABC is not a valid phone number or in our case one to three at gmail is not a valid
email.
Now in order to get started we're going to set up this attribute inside of our e-mail object.
Validate is going to be an object then we'll have the validate or set equal to a function.
The function gets called with the value to validate.
You either return true if it's valid or you return false.
If the value is invalid.
Next up we can set up our message.
I'm going to set message equal to a string.
We're going to inject the e-mail that was used and we'll say that e-mail is not a valid e-mail.
Excellent.
Now the only thing left to do to get this e-mail validation to work is actually install that third party
library and call the function inside of our validator.
The library itself is called validator it's an NPR module and you can find it by googling NPM validator.
It should be the first result.
What a handy little tip if you're ever trying to make sure that the Google search result is indeed the
result you want.
You can look at the L structure.
It's always package a forward slash package name which means that if you get a result like this one
which is forward slash validate you know it's the wrong library.
What you really want is the validator library.
Now the validator library has a ton of validations built in.
If you scroll down on the docs page you can see there's basically an endless list.
But the one they show off at the very beginning is the email method which is the one that we'll be using
for our purposes over inside of the terminal.
We can install the latest version of this module and PM install the module is called validator we'll
be installing the most recent version five point six point zero.
And I will use the same flag to update the package.
Jason File now that we have the module installed we can go ahead and move in to our model file and actually
implement it.
The first thing we need to do is import the library up above.
I'm going to change the VAR mongoose to a constant which I should have done in the first place.
Doesn't really matter but it is a good habit and I will also be creating a constant called the validator
said not equal to the return result from require and will be requiring that new library validator.
Now on here we have the is e-mail function it returns either true or false which means that right inside
of our custom function we can simply return validator.
Dot is email passing in de-value up above.
Now this function is going to return true if the email is valid it will return false if it's invalid.
And you might have noticed that we can actually make this even simpler.
Instead of getting the value in our custom function and passing it into his e-mail we can actually pass
in validator.
Dot is e-mail as is the method to use.
This is going to get passed the value and it will return true or false.
There is no reason to define a custom function.
This method will work on its own.
Now that we have our email property set up we can move down below and start setting up the password
attribute password which will be called Password is going to be a string.
So we'll go ahead and set the type equal to string.
We're also going to require it.
So all set required equal to true.
And last but not least we'll be setting the men length the minimum length of the plain text password.
In our case is going to be six although you could use a different value.
And this is all we need to do for password.
And nothing too complex here.
Next up we're going to specify the tokens property.
Now as I mentioned tokens is actually an array.
This is a feature available in Mongo D-B that is not available in Escuela databases like post gress
this nested document is going to be how we access the tokens for individual users in order to set up
the schema to support that we're going to set tokens equal to an array.
And we're going to provide one object inside of it.
This is the syntax that mongoose has set up for our purposes.
Now on this object we're going to specify all of the properties available on a token.
In our case it's access will set that equal to an empty object for the moment and token which will set
to an empty object as well.
Now we can go ahead and specify exactly what the access and token attributes should be.
In the case of access we're going to make sure that the type is a string and we'll go ahead and require
it by setting required equal to true required equal to true.
And we're going to have the exact same setup for tokin the type doesn't need to be a string and it will
be required so required will get set to true.
And this is all we need to do for the tokens array.
We're not going to be setting up any custom validation about the actual value for access or token that
will happen a little bit later it's going to be a little more complex because we do need to do a few
things with those values.
So we'll get to that in just a few videos.
For now though the user model is indeed complete.
We have our e-mail.
It's validated and it's unique.
We have our password it's validated and we have our tokens array.
This means it's time to actually create the request that a user is going to be able to hit to sign up
a new user that's going to happen over and server J.S..
And it's also going to be your challenge for this video.
This round is going to be a post HTP call post to forward slash users which is the exact same you are
all set up.
We had for creating new to do.
We want to create new users we post to users when we want to create new tattoos we post to to do is
to complete this route.
You can go ahead and use anything we've learned so far.
The most similar route we've created thus far would be the route to create a new to do the new to Duzer
out first creates a new instance of the model.
Then we go ahead and call save if things go well we return the doc if things go poorly we send back
the error.
This is exactly what you're going to need to do for the post user's request.
Now I'd also like you to use pick instead of pulling off the individual properties like we do up here.
Here we create a new object.
And on this object we just specify text what you're going to do instead is use pick like we do for the
patch method.
You're going to pick off the properties we want which will just be email and password.
This is going to give you the body variable and you can pass that into the constructor function directly.
Then you can call save and you can respond appropriately.
Whether it's successful or whether it's an error.
Now we have made some pretty big changes to the user model.
The most important change is that we have now made the email unique in order for this change to actually
work.
You're going to need to one that shut down your server to wipe the to do app database and 3 restart
the server.
If you do not wipe the database and restart the server it's not going to validate the emails to be unique
which is going to be a big problem.
Now once you're done I want you to play around with it.
Go ahead and make a valid request in post man then try to make the same request which should fail because
the e-mail will already be taken.
Try to play around with invalid emails and passwords as well.
Take a moment to pause the video.
Knock this out test it.
And when you're done.
Go ahead and click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to get all of that done I left it pretty open ended.
But the goal here is to set you out on your own when we're doing something we've already done before
and the code we're going to right here is indeed something we've done in the past.
The first thing I'm going to do is call at post to set up the post route and we'll pass in the U R L
board slash users.
Then we can set up our callback function with our request and response arguments.
Next up what I want you to do is use the pick method available on low dash to pull off the email and
password properties.
We're never going to let users manually update the tokens array.
They're not going to be able to directly access or manipulate this.
We're going to be manipulating this using a set of methods which will explore a bit later.
For now though all we're going to do is create a variable called Body setting and equal to the return
result from low dash dot pick.
And the syntax for pick if you remember is the first argument the object we want to pick from and the
second argument is an array.
We want to pick off two properties.
So we're going to add two items to the array the first one will be email and the second one will be
password.
Next up we can make a new instance of our user model a variable user will get the job done.
We'll set that equal to new user and we're going to pass in an object with the email and password properties.
Now we could recreate an object setting the email property equal to body email but we already have that
in-body so we can actually just pass it in like this.
There's no reason to pass in an object that we create when we already have the object we need.
Now obviously this is going to at most contain the email and password because we've picked those off
if any of them are missing like the is not provided.
It won't be provided here either.
So the validation will fail.
We don't need to worry about creating the object manually.
Next up we can call user data.
Which is actually going to try to save this document to the database.
Now that we have the document saved we can attach a then call back by calling then and we can specify
our success case.
We're going to get that user doc and we're going to be able to respond with it.
We'll be setting up authentication in this route later.
For now though a response send call passing back the user is going to get the job done.
The next thing to do and the last thing to do is set up a catch call here.
We're going to set up catch.
We're going to get that error and we're going to simply send it back.
Response dot status.
A 400.
Then we'll use dot send to send it back.
We'll send it back by sending back the air ject.
With this in place we are now done inside of Adam and we can move on to the next step which is going
to be to make sure our server is shut down and wipe the database in a rowboat.
Mongo.
I'm going to go ahead and drop the to do our database by clicking it and clicking drop database.
Now that the database is down we can head into the terminal and start up the server node server forward
slash server J.S. with the server now started on port three thousand over inside of post man.
We can test out the call by making a few requests.
I'm already in need to do app local environment and so that's good.
I can change the method from get to post and I can set up the R L which is available in an environment
variable from here all we need is forward slash users which is the route we just created.
We are going to be sending along some body data body raw.
Jason is going to let us do just that.
I can then go ahead and set up the Jason we're going to pass in those two properties.
Email will Saddam equal to a valid e-mail like Andrew at example dot com and password.
I'm going to set password for the moment equal to a valid password as well something with greater than
6 characters.
ABC 1 2 3.
Exclamation mark.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and send this off and when we send it off what do we
get back.
A 200 with the user object down below.
Now obviously our passwords are still in play in tax but that's fine for the moment.
The thing we're actually testing here is that the saving happened successfully.
Now if we keep the data exactly the same and send off another request you should get a 400 back this
400 is telling you that you have a duplicate key in the to do app users collection.
The email is already taken which is a pretty big problem if you're trying to sign up using that e-mail.
This is fantastic.
Next up we can test some other things like sending an invalid e-mail.
If I do that we're going to get a 400 back with a validation error if I try to send an invalid password.
Like the letter A.
We're also going to get an invalid password message down below with this in place we are now done.
Obviously the route is not complete.
We don't have authentication or password hashing set up but we have a pretty good basic version that
gets us going in the right direction.
I'm going to go ahead and save this request inside of our to do app postman collection before I do though
I will send it back to some valid data.
And you had example dot com and for the password I'll use password with the exclamation mark over here
I can now see that request using the exact same format we've used so far.
The method followed by the URL.
And we'll save it to the existing to do app collection.
I'm not going to be committing our changes just yet.
We're not quite done with the route so it doesn't make sense to commit them will be handling authentication
and password hashing in the next several videos after we're done with it then we'll make that commit
that does it for this one I will see you next time where we explore how exactly we're going to be authenticating
users.
Stay tuned.
We'll see you then