In this video you're going to learn about hashing in Jason Webb tokens using these techniques will be
able to set up authentication for our application.
Currently all of the routes down below getting to Doo's creating to do is getting an individual to do
leading to do's and updating to do's.
These are all public routes.
Anybody can hit these and manipulate data that wasn't necessarily created by them.
Once authentication is in place all these are going to be private routes meaning that you have to be
logged in and you can only manipulate data that you actually own which means I can't update to do that.
I didn't create.
Now in order to settle this up we're going to have to come up with some way to authenticate these requests
but we're going to do is create a token system.
This token you can think of it like a string is going to get sent back from our sign up and log in requests.
We don't have the log in one place just yet but we'll get to it soon.
The client is then going to take this token and use it to authenticate other requests.
They will simply pass it along as a hatter for example to a patch request and it will be able to make
that call successfully after authenticating.
Now in this video we're going to talk about hashing and authentication how to actually create that token
to get started over inside of the playground folder.
Let's make a file.
I'm going to call the file hashing dot J.S. and inside of hashing out yes we're going to get started
by playing around with a very basic hash function it's called shot 2:56.
Now in order to play around with this hash function we're going to need to install a module crypto J.S.
that includes all sorts of encryption and hashing algorithms some you might have heard of for example
abs M.D five or the one we're going to be using Shaw 256 to install it will run NPM I which is short
for install the module name is crypto hyphen SJS.
And we will be specifying the most recent version at three point one.
Point six with the Save flag.
This is going to go ahead and install the crypto Agellius module.
Once it's installed we can move in to our hashing file and import it.
I'm going to grab a certain property off of the require return result.
It's sha to 56 and the 256 comes from the number of bits that are the resulting hash.
Next up we'll set it equal to the return result from require.
And we're going to require that crypto J.S. module and now we have access to our hashing function to
hash a value all we have to do is pass it into the SHA 256 function.
I'm going to make a variable called message and all set equal to some string.
Something like I am user number three.
Then we can go ahead and actually hash it.
I'm going to make a variable called hash to store the result.
I'm going to call sha 2:56 passing in the value message.
Now the result is actually an object we're going to convert that to a string and using two string and
then we can go ahead and print both values to the screen using Konsole dot LOC console dialog.
I'll use template strings for both.
I'll print message Kolin followed by the actual message.
The message variable and I'll do the exact same thing for the hash.
I'm going to call console dialog with a template string in the hash colon space equals.
Then I'll inject the hash variable with this in place we can now run the hashing J S file and see what
we get over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to use clear to clear the terminal output.
We are going to run node and will going to be running a file in the playground folder.
The file itself is called hashing dot J Yes when we run it.
First up we got our message.
I am a user number three.
Then we get this really long string that looks random but I promise you it's not.
This is the hashed result of the message above.
Now hashing is fantastic hashing is a one way algorithm.
Meaning that given this message I am always going to get this result but I cannot get the original message
back.
If I have the result now I can prove that I'm always going to get the same result by simply rerunning
the file a few times.
I'm going to rerun it 4 times and what do I get.
I get the exact same hash value back because I passed in and the exact same hash value.
Now hashing is used in a ton of different situations.
For example storing passwords in a database.
It's a bad idea to store plain text passwords in a database.
So what a lot of people do is they salt and hash their passwords.
We'll talk about salting a little later but you already know what hashing is hashing is a way to obfuscate
the actual plain text password.
When someone goes to log in later they pass us the plaintext password.
We hash it getting their results and we compare that result to the result in the database.
If the two hashes are identical then the password is correct.
If they're not identical then the password must not have matched the one stored in the database.
Now we're going to be using hashing in a similar way to Web sites like source for each source forge
lets you verify that the file you downloaded is the one that you actually wanted because it hashes the
file and it shows you that hash value.
This means you can hash the file later if you get the same result.
You know it's the file Source Forge wanted you to get.
If you get a different result you know it's not the file that Source Forge wanted you to get and you
probably shouldn't use it because it could have viruses inside.
This is the exact technique that we'll be using for our token.
Now this is not going to prevent someone in the middle from seeing the value we're going to use HTP
ass for that will be securely transferring our tokens.
This is however going to prevent someone on the client who gets the value from manipulating the ID and
changing it to something else.
Let's say I send back a token and that token says this is for user number 3.
The user then gets the token and they change it to the number 4 and they try to delete someone else's
data.
What we can do is use hashing to make sure that that value the ID doesn't actually get changed if it
does we'll be able to spot that change and we'll be able to deny the user access because we know that
they never actually got that token from us.
They probably created the token on their own.
Now to illustrate how this is going to work let's talk about the data that we want to send back from
the server to the client.
We're going to make an object and we're going to call that object data and we'll set it equal to a regular
object for now specifying just one property ID.
The id property is going to equal the user's ID inside of the user's collection.
This is going to let us know which user should be able to make that request.
For example if I'm trying to delete a to do with an ID of 3 but the user who created that doesn't match
the idea of the token that I know that they shouldn't be able to delete that because it's not their
data.
Right here I'm going to set id equal to the number for excellent.
This is the data we want to send back to the client.
Now the important piece of the puzzle is going to be making sure that the client doesn't set 4 to 5.
Send the token back to us and say hey go ahead and delete all the to do's for user number 5.
That would be a really big security flaw.
So instead we're going to do as we are going to create a separate variable.
A variable called a token and this is what we're going to send back to the user.
The token variable is going to contain a data property that set equal to the data object defined above.
We can use yes 6 to make that definition.
Then we're going to go ahead and set a hash property.
The hash property is going to be the hash value of the data.
If the data changes later on and we rehash it we're not going to get the same value back so we'll be
able to tell that the data was manipulated by the client and we should not expect it to be valid.
Right here I'm going to set cash equal to the return result from Shaw to 56.
We're going to pass in the string now in this case we have an object so we can use Jason docstring ify
to convert our object to a string of Pasadena right here.
Then we can go ahead and call the two string method.
Storing the resulting hash on the hash property with this in place we now have a token.
Now this token is not foolproof.
For example let's say the user changes the data id property to 5.
All they have to do is rehash that data added onto the hash properties and the token back and they technically
would trick us.
What we're going to do to prevent this trickery is salt the hash salting a hash means you add something
on to the hash that is unique that changes the value.
For example if I hash the string password I'm going to get the same result every time.
But if I hash the string password with some sort of randomly generated value like this I'm going to
get a different result.
And as long as I use a different salt every single time I'm never going to get the same hash twice.
And this is exactly what we want we want to have a secret out add on to the end like a string.
Some secret will do for now.
And this is going to salt our hash.
Now the user the client they're not going to be able to manipulate this data anymore.
They could change the ID from four to five.
They could try to rehash but they're not going to have the secret so their hash is going to be bad.
When we then try to verify the hash later on we're going to see that the data and the hash don't quite
add up because the person who manipulated it didn't have the secret and will be able to deny access
for that request.
Let's take a look at how we would validate that this tokin was not manipulated down below.
I'm going to create a variable called result hash this will store the hash of the data that comes back
the data that may or may not have been manipulated.
I'm going to set it equal to SHA 2:56 passing in the actual data.
This is accessible via Jason docstring if I tokin dot data.
We're going to access the data property.
We're going to hash it.
And we're also going to use the exact same salt some secret.
Now we're going to go ahead and call to strenge on the results so we can get back our string value and
we can make some comparisons if the result hash equals using triple equals the token hash property then
we know that data was not manipulated because if it was the hash would not equal the hash provided because
of the salt.
This means that we can use console log to print data was not changed if the hashes do not equal each
other then we know the data was changed and we should not trust it because it's most likely not correct
data was changed.
Don't trust
us now that we have our two messages in place we can go ahead and rerun this file from the terminal.
And what do we get.
We get data out was not changed and it wasn't right between here where we could have changed the data.
We never did.
Now we can go ahead and actually change the data to make sure that the call fails down below after that
change.
We should get data was changed do not trust the men in the middle.
They might try to do something like this.
I might try to change the token data ID property to five let's say on user form really mad at user 5
I want to wipe all their data.
I would change the ID and then I would also create the hash token hash is now going to equal the hash
of the new data shock 256 will pass in.
Jason docstring ify to convert our object into a string.
We have that object it's in tokin dot data.
Then we're going to go ahead and call two strings.
Now this is where the salt comes into play the person in the middle.
The person on the client trying to manipulate that data.
They do not have access to the same salt.
They don't know that secret because the secret is only on the server which means when they try to rehash
and update tokened out hash to a new value it's not going to match the hash that we create later on.
And we'll be able to tell that the data was changed.
If I rerun the file this time around we can see data was changed do not trust.
If I comment out these lines and rerun run it what do we get.
Well I never say the files get the same result.
But if I save the file and rerun it this time we see data was not changed and that is fantastic.
We don't have a way to make sure that the data right here was never changed.
In our case this is going to be the token we pass back and forth.
Now this concept that we just went over the idea of creating an object hashing it and verifying it later.
This is not something new.
There's actually a whole standard it's called the Jasen web tokin and this is exactly what we're going
to be implementing inside of our application.
We could write all this code out and handle all the edge cases but there's no reason to do that.
There's a standard in place with libraries that make adding JWT short for Jason Webb tokens or port
really really easy.
I'm going to comment out all of the code we have so far both examples and we're going to go ahead and
install this new library.
We're not going to be using the crypto JSA library inside of our actual application.
This was for playground purposes only.
The next library and Jason Webb token we are going to be using inside of our actual application code
over in the terminal we can use clear to clear the terminal output.
I'm going to run NPM I.
The module name is Jason Wehbe token and we're looking for the version at seven point 1.9 which is the
latest version and I'll be using the Save flag.
Now we can go ahead and actually run the installer installing the module and we can play around with
it over inside of hashing out.
Yes essentially what we get is two functions one to create the token and one to verify it.
Instead of adding all this code with the if else statements we just simply call these two utility functions.
It's really painless.
It's truly a fantastic library right here.
I'm going to make a concert at the top of the file calling it JWT and sending an equal to the return
result from requiring Jason Webb tokin.
Now there are two methods we're going to use are JWT ADOT sign and just below that JWT dot varify JWT
sign as you might expect takes the object in this case the data with the user ID and it signs it.
It creates that hash and then it returns the token value.
Now JWT varified does the opposite.
It takes that token and the secret.
And it makes sure that data was not manipulated.
Let's go ahead and call it right now.
I'm going to recreate our data variable of our data set it equal to the object with the ID and also
the ID to the number 10.
For the moment perfect.
Now we can go ahead and call sign the sign method takes the object in our case we have that as the data
variable and it takes your secret I'm going to make our secret one two three A B C.
Now the call to sign it is going to return our token.
We're going to want to store that in a variable called token.
I'm going to comment out the other line and this this is the value we're going to send back to the user
when they either sign up or log in.
It's also the value we're going to store inside of that tokens array access will equal the string off
and the token will equal the token.
We just generated now that we signed our data we can go ahead and print it to the screen and take a
look at what we get council Lague token.
I'm going to head into the terminal and use clear and then I'll rerun the file through node and send
the playground folder and it's called hashing.
Yes what do we get.
We get another long the cryptographic looking strain and that's exactly what it is.
This string stores all of the information we need to verify that the data the data right here was never
manipulated.
Now if you want to take a look at exactly what makes up a JWT you can take the value.
I'm going to copy it from the terminal.
You can go to your browser and head over to J.
W.T..
I know JWT Io has a bunch of documentation and explanations about how Jason Webb tokens work but on
the home page they also have a really cool tool over on the left.
We can paste in our token.
I'm going to delete the existing value and paste the value in.
On the right we can see information about that token.
There's three main parts to a JWT.
We're only going to be editing the payload.
We have the header which stores things like the algorithm that was used in this case.
As 2:56 is used and we add the type.
It's a Jason Webb tokin.
And the payload we have the thing we set.
We set the ID to 10 and we have the issued at time stamp which tells us when the token was created this
is really useful data down below.
We have the verification.
This is where the actual algorithm is executed.
This is where the hash is stored.
Now you'll notice right now I have an invalid signature down below.
That's because the Secret right here is different from the secret.
I used to create the hash over inside of atom.
I used one two three.
ABC if I change this text box to 1 to 3 ABC now I had the signature as verified.
This is what makes up a token.
Everything before the first dot is the Hatter.
And between that second and third dots that's the payload.
That's our information.
And the last part is the hash which allows us to verify that the payload was never changed.
Now that we have our token we can go ahead and learn how to verify that it was not altered.
JWT verify is the function that's going to let us get that done.
We're going to call it passing in the token we want to verify.
And we're going to be passing in the exact same secret.
It has to be the same.
Otherwise it will not be validated.
And what do we got.
We're going to get the decoded results.
I'm going to create a variable called Decoded and print it to the screen console dialog.
The first argument will be the string Decoded.
So it's easier to find in the terminal and the second one will be the actual decoded variable.
With this in place over inside of the terminal I can now rerun the file and right here we get our token
which we got earlier and we get our data.
We have our decoded data where the ID is 10 now.
Anything about the secret or the token changes before we call verify the call is not going to pass.
We're going to get an error.
For example let's manipulate the data by concatenating on the number one then we can rerun the file
and what do we get.
We get an error.
It's an invalid signature.
The data inside of that token is not what we expected.
It's been changed and you should not trust it.
If the secret is incorrect I'm going to add another C onto the end and you rerun the file.
What do we get.
We get the exact same error.
JWT is letting you know that something's not right with the data.
Only when the token is unaltered and the secret is the same as the one used to create the token.
Are we going to get the data back and this is exactly what we want.
Once we decode the data after the person makes the request with the token we can use that ID to start
actually doing the thing the user wants to do.
Whether it's creating a to do updating one deleting one or any other data manipulation.
I know that was a long video so thanks for bearing with me.
But it's really important that you understand hashing and the JWT concept now that we have both of these
down.
We can actually implement them into our application which is going to let us authenticate requests which
is the real purpose of this section.
Thanks again for bearing with me.
Hopefully you enjoyed it.
Stay tuned I will see you next time