And now that you know a bit about hashing and Jason Webb tokens Let's start integrating that into the
to do API in the first place we're going to integrate that is inside of our post.
Users Sign-Up call.
Currently we do not return an authentication token which is not cool.
The users shouldn't need to sign up and then make a separate logging request.
They just signed up give them a token back.
Now we could indeed put all of the code for generating this Jason web token right here inside of our
express route handler.
But we're going to be reusing this code in multiple places both the sign up and log in express routes.
They're both going to require this functionality.
So it makes a lot more sense to break this out into a reusable method that we can take advantage of
in both.
There are two types of methods.
We're going to be exploring in this video.
We're going to be exploring model methods and instance methods model methods are called on the upper
case you a user object an instance methods are called on an individual user.
Like the new user we just created right here.
A good example of an instance method will be creating in this video is a method called generate auth
token The generate auth token method is going to be responsible for adding a token on it to the individual
user document saving that and returning the token.
So we can send it back to the user.
This requires the individual document in order to work.
We can generate a token if we don't have access to things like the user id and access to updating that
individual user.
So we can add the token to its tokens array.
Your model methods on the other hand do not require an individual document.
A good example of a model method would be something like.
Find by token find by token it doesn't exist inside a mongoose find by one does find it does but find
by token is going to be a custom model method.
We're going to create.
It's going to take that JWT token that the user sends in one of their secure requests we're going to
find the individual user and we'll return that user to the caller.
Both of these are going to be really useful in getting authentication done.
For now though we're going to stick with just creating our generate auth token method over inside of
the user model file before we can even do that.
We do have to make one quick tweak.
Now the tweak I'm about to make is not going to update the functionality of the app at all.
We're simply restructuring our app for flexibility in order to add on these methods.
We have to switch how we create our user model.
I'm going to delete this commented out code as it's no longer useful and we're going to make a variable
called user schema.
The user schema variable is going to store the schema for a user which means it's going to store all
of the properties kind of like the ones we've defined right here.
Now I don't mean kind of like I mean identical to right here.
We're going to set user schema equal to a new schema in mongoose that is done by using the new keyword
going onto the mongoose object and accessing the uppercase as schema property.
The schema property lets you define a new schema and this is what we need in order to tack on these
custom methods.
We can't add methods on to user so we have to switch how we're generating the model.
Now the schema constructor function it takes an object and on that object we define all of the attributes
for our document.
We actually have all of those defined right here.
We can literally take this object cut it out and replace it right here.
Now we have our schema and the only thing we need to do to restore the old functionality is pass it
in as the second argument user schema.
At this point we have made zero changes to the functionality of our application.
We simply restructured allowing us to out on these methods to create a method right below where we define
the user schema.
I'm going to add something on to user schema dot methods user schema methods as an object and on this
object we can add any method we like.
These are going to be your instance methods.
In our case we're going to be adding an instance method called generate auth token your instance methods
do have access to the individual document which is great because we need that information in order to
create our Jason Webb took it.
Now we're going to set the secret to a function but I also notice I'm not going to be using an arrow
function.
I'm going to be using a regular old function with the function keyword.
Now as you've noticed throughout the course I've mostly used aero functions era functions that do not
bind a.
This keyword we need.
This keyword for our methods.
Because the this key word stores the individual document which means that we can actually create a variable
called user setting an equal to this by doing this.
It's a lot more clear exactly what we're manipulating.
Instead of manipulating this which could be anything we're simply going to be manipulating the user
which is an identifier that we're used to in other places in our file.
Now that we have access to the individual document the document where the method was called on for example
this document we're going to be able to define what we want to do.
Over inside of user dot J s we can now fill this out.
We need to get an access value and a token value in order to create the new token inside of the document.
First up access really simple a variable called Access which gets set equal to the string off.
Nothing fancy there.
Next up though we are going to be making our token variable which means we're going to need to use that
same JWT sign method we used over in the hashing file to generate the token before we can actually call
JWT sign.
We do need to require it up at the very top of the file.
I'm going to make a constant.
I'm going to call this constant JWT and we'll set it equal to the return result from requiring Jason
Webb tokin.
Now that we have JWT in place we can call it down below setting the token equal to J.
W.T. dot sign.
We're going to call sign with those two arguments the first one being the object that has the data we
want to sign.
And the second one being some secret value we're eventually going to take this secret value out of our
code and move it into a configuration variable.
But for now you can add some secret value.
I'm going to use ABC 1 2 3.
The actual data we want to sign is first up the user ID are going to create an underscore ID property
to store this value and we can grab it off of user like we would anywhere else in our server file user
dot underscore ID dot to hack's string.
We want to pass in the string value as opposed to the object ID.
And the other property we're going to be adding on is access.
I can use yes 6 to add the access property setting an equal to the Access variable which is the string
off.
Now this returns our object I'm going to call to string to get back our string token.
Now all of our data is generated and all we need to do is update the user tokens array.
It's a regular array which means we can use regular array methods to manipulate it.
But I'm going to do is call user Dom tokens which is an empty array by default dot push which lets us
push on something new.
In this case we're going to be pushing on a new object with those two properties access and tokin we
have access and token variables defined right here which means we can use the yes 6 object definition
syntax specify access and specify token a few students have reported running into issues using push
push was causing problems when they actually ran the script and I dug into it a little bit and there
are some inconsistencies across Mongo D-B database versions.
So what we have is a new line.
What I'd like you to do is replace that push like the one we just wrote with the second line shown here.
Here we get the exact same thing done adding a new item.
We just do it via the concat method as opposed to the push method and this does work across a wider
range of versions.
This is the method that I recommend you use so swap out this line and that's it.
Let's go ahead and jump right back in.
With this in place we now have changes made to the user model.
The last thing to do is actually save those changes.
Currently we update the local user model but we do not save it in order to save it.
We're going to call user dot save no user not save as we know returns a promise which means we can call
datt then right here I can pass in my success callback function and all we're going to do is return
the token.
This is the variable we defined above.
And we're going to do this so later on in the server file we can grab the token by tacking on another
then call back getting access to the token and then responding inside of the callback function.
Now this Denn statement this is going to happen in server J.S. in order to allow server J to chain on
to the promise we're going to return it right here.
Now you might never have seen this done before.
Usually when you return to chain in a promise you return another promise.
In this case though we're just returning a value and that is perfectly legal.
That value will get passed as the success argument for the next then call.
In our case we are done with the user dot J.S. file and we can move on to server.
J.S. actually generating the token by calling the method and adding it as a header.
I'm going to save this file and over in server J.S. we're going to kick things off right inside of our
Save callback instead of responding right here.
We're going to call that method.
We're going to call user dot generate auth token.
It doesn't take any arguments so we won't call it with any.
Then we can go ahead and return it since we know that we're expecting a chaining promise and we can
tack on a another then call back.
I'm going to add a second to then call back right here and this is going to get called with the token
value.
Now we have everything we need to make the response we have the user end we have the token right here
inside of our.
Then callback function.
We're going to respond by calling response dot send sending back the user.
Now we've already added this part of the code.
It was done up here.
And you'll notice the user variable that we sent back is not the same as the user variable defined here
up above.
We used the user variable which was the argument to then but this value is identical to the one up here.
And I don't mean that the actual objects have the same value.
I mean they're literally the same exact thing in memory which means we can simply remove the argument
right here.
This just clears up what's happening and doesn't change the functionality at all.
Now it's really clear that we can go ahead and send back the user because the only user variable is
defined right here.
Next up we have to add on that header we have to send the token back as an HTP response header which
is the real goal here.
To do that we call a dot on the response object hetter takes two arguments.
The arguments are key value pairs.
The key is that he had her name and the value is the value you want to set the header to our header
name is going to be X hyphen Auth..
When you prefix a header with X hyphen you're creating a custom header which means it's not necessarily
a header that HTP supports by default.
It's a header that you're using for our specific purposes in our application for example we're using
a JWT token scheme.
So we're creating a custom header to store that value.
Next up we can go ahead and pass in the value which is just going to be the token argument up above.
With this in place we can now remove the old commented out response and we are done in order to test
that everything is working as expected.
We're going to start up the server and fire off a few requests over inside of postman I'm going to start
up the server by running node server forward slash server dot.
J.S. once the server is up on port three thousand we can move in post man and try to sign up a new user.
I'm going to use the post user's method and I am going to be updating e-mail inside of the body data.
Since this email is already in use instead of Andrew I'll use Andrew A B C.
Now I can go ahead and send off this request making sure I'm on the to do app a local environment.
And what do I get back down below.
I get back a 200 down below.
You can see the entire user document which for the moment is a problem that will fix that in a second.
We have an access value the token value.
We have a unique ID for this object.
All inside of the tokens array over inside of the headers tab.
We can also see the response headers that came back and right here we have our X Auth. a value.
This is the J W T value that we're going to need to send with our secure requests like posting it to
do getting to Doo's or deleting to do's that'll be done a little bit later but for now we do indeed
have the Tokin getting sent back.
Now one thing we can take care of really quickly is limiting the data that comes back when we convert
one of our instances one of our users into a Jason value.
There is a two adjacent method available that we can actually override which means we can only send
back certain values for the case of a user.
We really only want to send back the ID and the email we should go ahead and leave off things like the
password and the tokens array.
These are secure properties that should never ever get sent back to the user because they have no reason
for them in order to do this over inside of Adam.
We're going to override a method previously we created a method we created that generate auth token
method right here.
But we can also override a method to update exactly how mongoose handles certain things.
User schema methods is going to be where we store this method once again and the method is called to
uppercase Jason.
This method which we're going to define as a regular function determines what exactly gets sent back
when a mongoose model is converted into a Chaisson value.
In our case we're going to first grab the value then we'll use the underscore pick method to actually
pick off the properties we want to send back.
First up I'm going to make a variable called user sending an equal to this just like we do for generate
or token and then we can go ahead and create a variable called user object the user object is to get
set equal to user dot to object user Dom to object is responsible for taking your mongoose variable
user and converting it into a regular object where only the properties available on the document exist.
Now that we have this user object variable we can use pick.
I'm going to return a low dash dot pick picking off some properties from the user object and the properties
that we'll be picking off will be inside of the array underscore ID.
And as the second item in the array.
Email this means we'll be leaving off things like the password and the tokens array which should not
get returned and we are going to need to import low Dasch up above since we're using the pick method.
Konst underscore equals require low dash.
Awesome.
Now we can go ahead and restart the server and making new Sign-Up request and see what data comes back
in.
The response body over in the terminal log in my server a quick restart then inside of postman I can
go ahead and change the e-mail to something that doesn't exist like ABC C send off the request and down
below we get it 200.
And this time we get a trimmed version of the document.
We only get back the user id and the e-mail which is exactly what we wanted.
Over inside of the headers section we do still get back the token which is great.
This is what the user is going to need in order to authenticate later.
With this in place we are now done the same method is looking great and knows how to sign up users and
it knows how to generate these auth tokens.
Since we have something meaningful complete Let's go ahead and make a commit to our Get repository over
inside of the terminal.
I'm going to shut down the server and run get status right here.
You can see we have our changed files as well as our new file.
I'm going to run and get added to add all of those to the next commit and get commit to actually make
that commit ad post the users route and tokin method.
Once the commit is made we can go ahead and push it up to get Hobb going to avoid deploying to Heroku
for the moment sends there's nothing Heroku specific we need to test out yet we'll deploy to her Al-Q
a little later when we actually have a couple routes complete and that is it for this one I will see
you next time as we continue on with authentication.