In this video you're going to learn how to turn your express routes into private routes.
This means that will require an X off tokin.
We're going to validate that tokin we're going to find the user associated with that token then and
only then will you actually be able to run the route code.
Now we're going to be making a lot of routes private.
So what I want to do is make it as easy as possible to take a route like this one and turn it into a
private route to do that.
We're going to add some express middleware that does all of that validation and verification for us.
That's going to make it dead simple to turn any one of our routes into a private route.
Obviously we will have public routes like the sign up line.
It doesn't make sense to make this private.
Otherwise no one could ever sign up.
Now to illustrate exactly how this is going to work we're going to make a brand new route an app and
dots get to route.
We'll use the HTP get method to access this one in the U R L is going to be forward slash users forward
slash me.
This route is going to require authentication which means you're going to need to provide a valid X
auth token.
It's going to find the associated user and it's going to send that user back much like we send the user
back up above sending back the ID and e-mail.
This will be our very first private route and then we'll take the lessons learned here to make some
middleware so we can easily turn all of the routes above into private routes.
The first thing we need to do is specify our callback function where we get the request and response
objects and inside of here we're going to start by grabbing the token we can make a variable called
token and we can set it equal to the return result from request dot hatter.
Now Everquest is pretty similar to response dot Hetter response that lets us set a header.
So it takes the key value request header is getting the value.
So we only need to pass in that key the X off header variable is the value we want to fetch.
Now we'll have that inside of Tokin and we can go ahead and actually verify that token fetch the user
and do something with it.
Now once again this is going to be code we use in multiple places.
So we're going to turn it to our user schema and create a model method the model method is going to
be accessed via uppercase user and it's going to be called Find a by token find by token is going to
take the token value and it's going to find the appropriate user related to that token returning it
inside of your promise callbacks.
This means we'll be able to do something with the document of the user associated with the token.
Now in order to get started down this path we obviously need to define this model method over inside
of user dot.
And that's what we're going to do first down below and below our generate auth token method.
We're going to define our model method.
This one gets created by calling users schema but instead of accessing dot methods we're going to access
ADOT statics dot statics as an object kind of like methods although everything you add onto it turns
into a model method as opposed to an instance method.
Right here I'm going to set the statics property find by token now find by token is going to be a regular
function using the function keyword because once again we do need access to this binding.
And unlike our other methods it's also going to take an argument it's going to take that token now that
we have the token we can go through the process of verifying it finding the associated user and returning
it.
The first thing I'm going to do is create a variable called user with an upper case you and set it equal
to this instance methods get called with the individual document model methods get called with the model
as the.
This binding now that we have our User variable in place we can make a variable called Decoded Decoded
which I'm going to set to undefine for the moment is going to store the decoded JWT values.
This is going to be the return result from JWT to verify which we used over and hashing dot J ass right
here.
I'm creating an undefined variable and I'll tell you why in just a second.
The reason why is because the JWT varify function is going to throw an error if anything goes wrong.
If the secret doesn't match the secret the token was created with or if the token value was manipulated.
That means we want to be able to catch this error and do something with it to do that.
We're going to use a try catch block that's a try block followed by the cache keyword which gets called
with this error arguments and we have the catch block right here.
Now if you haven't use try catch blocks they're pretty great if any errors happen in the try block.
The code automatically stops execution and moves into the catch block.
It lets you run some code there then it continues on with your program.
In our case the code that we want to test is JWT.
Verify.
We want to see if this throws an error.
Now are going to set the result equal to the decoded variable and we're going to pass in our two arguments.
The actual token we want to decode and the secret.
Now once again the secret is currently stored in the code.
We'll be changing that later but for now we can simply pass in the exact same value.
ABC 1 2 3.
Just like this.
Now if this fails we're obviously going to add something into catch but we're going to do that in a
little bit.
For now I want to move on to what happens in the success case.
If we are able to successfully decode the token that was passed in as the header we are going to call
user and not find one to find the associated user if any.
Now this is going to return a promise and we are going to return that in order to add some chaining.
That means we can add a then call on to find by token over in server.
J.S. Right here.
We're going to call find one with our query and for the first time we're going to need to query our
nested object properties inside of tokens.
We have an array.
We have a token an access property we need to find users whose values match the ones that we have right
here.
The first one we're looking for is the ID.
Nothing new there.
We're looking for a user where the underscore ID property equals the one inside of Decoded decoded underscore
ID.
Next up we need to find a user whose tokens array has an object where the token property equals the
token property we have right here to query a nested document.
What we're going to do is wrap our value in quotes and then we're going to specify tokens dot token.
This lets us query that value.
We want to find one where it's equal to the token argument passed in above.
And we're going to do the exact same thing for access.
We're looking for a user where in their tokens array the access property is set to off.
Now off is going to be the string there is no Auth. variable saw wrap it in quotes.
Now to keep things consistent I am going to wrap this idea in quotes as well.
You don't need to do that but sense quotes are required when we have a dot in the value.
I need them here so I might as well use them up above.
Now with this in place are fine by token method has its success case handled.
We still haven't handled any errors but that's fine for the moment.
We can continue on inside of server.
J.S. Right here.
I'm going to tack on a then call back this callback is going to get called with the user.
It might be Knol if there is no user that passed the query.
So we'll have to check for that as well.
If there is no user
We're going to do something and we're going to do that in just a moment.
For now we're going to stick with that happy path on the happy path.
The last thing we do is we respond with the user.
That means I'm going to call response send passing in the user document.
Now obviously the call is not complete but we can go ahead and save both of these files and it should
work if we pass in a valid X auth token and that's all we care about.
For the moment over inside of robo Mongo I'm going to go ahead and wipe my databases since I have a
lot of weird data.
I'm going to refresh the connection take the to do app database and simply drop it.
Now over inside the terminal I can start up the server node server server J.S. and I can move into post
man to create a user over inside of postman.
I'm going to make a post user's request using the default data where the email is and you're at example
dot com.
I'm going to send out this request and everything works as expected.
We got our user back and we get our Hetter value.
Now I'm going to go ahead and copy this X off hetter value because we need to use it for our next request.
It's going require me to go to the right and make sure I grab the entire thing not just the visible
part.
Now I can go ahead and make a separate request by creating a new tab.
This one is going to be to the environment variable.
You Arel like all the other ones are.
And the you R-AL is forward slash user's forward slash meet.
Now this call is going to fail if we don't pass a token because we haven't set up the error handler
just yet.
So I am going to provide the x value and the tab will set X hyphen Auth. equal to the value we just
copied from the response.
Then I can go ahead and send this off.
And what do we get.
We get our user back and this is fantastic.
We get users me route requires an X off value it's not going to work if you don't provide one.
Now obviously we provided a valid token here.
Let's go ahead and write some code that makes things work.
When the token is valid over inside of atom we're going to kick things off in user.
J.S. Right here in this catch block we're going to do is return a promise that's always going to reject
it this code runs we never want this code to run right here.
I am going to return a new promise then we're going to pass in our function.
Remember the promise gets called with resolve and reject.
This can be an arrow function and inside of here all I'm going to do is call reject.
This means that this promise will get returned from fine by tokin.
Then over inside of server it'll get rejected.
So our then success case will never fire the catch call back window so we can add one right here.
An attack on a catch callback it'll get called with some error.
And this is where we'll have that code now inside of the catch call back all we're going to do is send
back a 401.
Status the 401 status means authentication is required if we get an error.
That means clearly they didn't authenticate correctly.
We can do that using response ADOT status setting the status equal to 4 0 1 and sending back an empty
body.
Now inside of user J s this code can actually be simplified.
Instead of returning a new promise then rejecting it right away.
We can actually return promise dot reject this does the exact same thing only it is a heck of a lot
simpler.
I could also pass in a value if I want to reject with some value that value would get used as the argument
right here.
Now over inside of user we are going to stick with this reject method.
I'm going to go ahead and remove the commented out code the much longer version and there we go find
by tokened is officially complete inside of server.
Yes we still have one case that we need to fix.
If there is no user This means there is a valid token but for some reason the query could not find a
document that matched the parameters we specified.
In that case we want to respond with the exact same thing.
We want to send back a 401.
Now we could go ahead and use response dot status with the 401.
And send back an empty body.
But that's the exact same thing we have down below.
A better technique would be to return promise not reject just like we did in the other file.
Now the function is automatically going to stop.
So this code will never get executed.
We're going to run the error case and we're going to send back a 4.
0 1 which is exactly what we want with this in place.
We can now test that our new code is working.
I'm going to go ahead and save both files over inside of the terminal.
Give things a restart and inside of postman we can now make the exact same request.
It's valid.
Let's go ahead and change it.
I'm going to change the e to and send it off.
And what do we get we get our 401.
Unauthorized.
I can also remove X off altogether send that off.
And we also get a 401.
On authorized.
Which is fantastic.
Now this call is going to be something we use over and over again.
So I am going to set off equal to the string test and I'll save it in my to do app collection.
I'm going to use Save As I'll change the request name to get users.
Me and I'm going to save it to our existing to do app collection so we can fire it off much quicker
later on.
Now that we have our one route privatized we want to break out this code into some middleware.
So all of our routes can take advantage of it without having to actually run all of these function calls
for the moment.
We're going to define our middleware function right here although it will be moved into its own file.
We can make a function we can call it authenticate and this is going to be the middleware function that
we use on our routes to make them private.
Now if you remember from the middleware section we get three arguments the request the response and
next the actual route is not going to run until next gets called inside of the middleware.
Then we can tack on the rest of the Aero function and we can get started.
Now this function is actually going to look really really similar to the one we have down below.
So I'm going to take it copy it and paste it inside of authenticate making just a few changes.
Now we do still want to grab the token value.
This line is perfectly fine and we do still want to find the user by tokin.
Next up we do still want to reject if there is an error but right here instead of sending back the user
what we're going to do is modify the request object.
This means that we'll be able to use the modified request object inside of the route down below to add
the middleware will simply reference the function right here and now this route will be using the middleware
defined up above.
Instead of sending back a response we're going to set request dot user equal to the user We just found.
And we're also going to request a dot token equal to the token up above.
Now that we have a request modified we're going to able to use that data by accessing it right here.
This means that what we can do down below is remove all of this code and simply call response send sending
back the user which is available on request dot user.
Now right here after we modify the request object we do need to call next.
Otherwise the code down below in this function will never actually execute.
Right here we are still going to send back a 401.
If anything goes wrong we do want to respond.
And we're not calling next because we don't want to run this code.
If the authentication didn't work as expected.
Now that we have this in place we have the exact same functionality only we have it in a really reusable
function.
I'm going to go ahead and break this out into its own folder and file inside of server.
We'll make a new directory.
I'm going to call this new directory middleware and inside of middleware we'll make a file called authenticate
J.S. and all we're going to have an authenticator.
J S is our middleware function.
I'm going to cut it out a server J paste paste inside of here and now all we need to do is import the
user.
Since that is not currently accessible inside of this file I'm going to make a variable that variable
will pull off user from the return value just like we did earlier.
Then we're going to have a relative path.
We need to go up a directory.
Then we're going to go into the models directory and we're going to grab that user file models spelled
incorrectly.
M o d e l.
That's excellent.
Now we have our imports in place the last thing to do is export authenticate.
I'm going to set module exports equal to an object and that object will simply authenticate equal to
the authenticate variable defined above.
Now that are authenticate file is complete.
We can load it in in server JSA and access the middleware just like we have right here up above at the
very top of the file we can get this done.
I'm going to do it just below where we have our user inport.
We're going to make a variable.
We're going to pull off authenticate then we're going to require it using the relative path we need
to go into that middleware directory that we just created.
And we're going to grab the authenticate file leaving off the JS extension now that we have the authenticate
variable imported it is going to be used right here and they get route for fetching the currently authenticated
user will work just as it did before.
I'm going to go ahead and save all of my files restart things over in the terminal and make one final
request in postman to verify everything works.
Now I am going to need to create a new user since I lost access to that token.
Actually I think it is still sitting over here.
Perfect.
I'm going to grab the old token from the other tab if you don't have it you can always sign up a new
user that I'm going to go to get users me paste it in here and send off my request we get to 200 and
we get the user object which means everything is working as expected when the token gets processed it
properly calls it the actual route handler.
We get the request user right here and we send it back.
Now if the token is a bad value I'm going to delete some keys and we send that off.
We're still getting the correct errors so everything is looking great now that we have this in place
we have our first private route which is just fantastic.
I'm going to wrap this video up by making a comment to save our changes.
Let's shut down the server and run it get status.
Here we have our modified user file.
The server file and our new middleware file.
I can use get added to add all of those to the next commit that I can use and get commit with the flag
to make the commit ad get users.
Me and authentication middleware
and there we go.
I'm going to push that up to get help.
And we are done.
We've made some really good progress towards authentication.
We all have a way to generate tokens and we have a way to verify those tokens creating private routes
in the next video we're going to continue on working through authentication.
I'm super excited to get to it.
So stay tuned.
I will see you next time