In this video you're going to learn how to hash users passwords before saving them to the database which
means a user is still going to send the plain text password in the post user's request.
You will still validate the plain text version making sure it's of a certain length then you're going
to hash it salted and store it in the database.
This is much more secure than what we're currently doing which is storing that plain text password which
is a terrible idea.
Now in order to get this hashing done we're going to use an algorithm called the script to be script
is fantastic because it is super secure and it has salting built in.
Which means you don't need to go through the effort to write the code to solve your passwords.
You can simply take advantage of the B crypt algorithm.
Now to install this over inside of the terminal we're going around NPM.
I was at the module name.
There are quite a few different variations of the B crypt algorithm on NPM.
I always use the crypt J.S. and this library is completely written inside of javascript which means
there are no dependencies.
There is also a library called B crypt which has the same API but I run into so many problems with that
especially across operating systems.
B crypt dot J.S. at the most recent version 2.0 3.0 and I'm going to tack on the Save flag to add it
to my package.
Jason File.
Now before we actually add this to the application let's just play around with B crypt really quickly
over in the hashing J.S. file over inside of hashing.
J.S. we can comment out all the other examples we have.
You can feel free to delete these or keep them.
This is going to be one of the last times we actually edit this file.
Up the very top.
We are going to load in the algorithm.
Let's make a constant called B crypt and set it equal to the return result from requiring B crypt J
S.
Now if you want to look at the docs you can always head over to NPM.
Let me just point you in the right direction.
Really quickly.
B crypt.
J.S. NPM should get you the right result.
And here it is.
It's the NPM package B crypt dot J.
This module has fantastic documentation.
So if you ever want to read more about the algorithm or see all of the other methods that are available
to you it's all defined here.
Now in order to use a B script J.S. inside of a hashing file we need to do two things.
First we have to get some sort of value.
Let's make a variable we'll call it password and we'll set it equal to 1 to 3 A B C.
Exclamation mark and then we're going to go ahead and actually hash it.
Now in order to hash a password using the script we have to call two methods.
One is Jeon salt.
This is going to generate a salt.
We can use to salt our password.
The other one is the hash method which actually goes through the hash in process.
Now sorting passwords is really important.
Imagine to have a password like password one if I hashed out without salting it I'm going to get the
same result every time.
Let's just say for example purposes the result is an an end.
Now obviously that's not the case but this is just an example.
Now the problem with this strategy is someone can precompile a list of passwords and hashed values and
they can use that as a lookup table.
They can say hey I've ran through 15000 English words including password 1 and I had the hash values
for all of them in an object where the key is the password and the value is the actual hash.
All I need to do is find the one that matches m and n and boom they have your password.
When you sult a password.
You're adding a bunch of random characters to that hash.
This means that even if I hash the same password multiple times I'll get a different result.
So no one can precomputed table to look at the passwords.
Now in order to generate that salt we're going to call the crypt dot Janise salt.
Jen salt takes two arguments.
It's an asynchronous function the second argument is a callback function and the first one is the number
of rounds you want to use to generate the salt.
If the crypt is inherently slow and that's a good thing it's going to prevent brute force attacks.
We're going to use 10 as the number of rounds.
The bigger the number the longer the algorithm is going to take.
I know people who use 120 rounds they intentionally make the crypt take longer.
So no one can brute force these calls.
Now obviously adding unnecessary length to your API is not a great idea but what it comes to passwords.
It definitely is.
This is going to prevent someone from making a million requests every second.
Instead they may be able to make a few hundred which is going to greatly reduce the chance that they'll
be able to crack a password.
Now we're going to generate this salt passing in our callback function.
We'll get an error and a salt value and then we can go ahead and finish off the Aero function and end
here this is where we're going to actually do the hashing decrypt dot hash and inside of here we're
going to pass in three arguments.
The first one is the thing to hash in our case.
We're going to be hashing the password.
We have that variable declared right here.
The second is the salt to use.
We have the salt.
We just generated it via the function up above.
The third is the callback function the callback function is going to get called with an error if any.
And the hash value this hash value is what we want to store inside of our database.
We don't want to store the password.
We want to store the hash.
Let's go out and log this to the screen using console log and simply passing in hash that I'm going
to go ahead and run the hashing file inside of the terminal.
I'll use clear to clear the terminal output and we can run node playground forward slash hashing.
J.S. when I do this.
I get my hashed value.
Now this hash value has a lot of really awesome information stored inside of it and as the number of
rounds you can see we have 10 right here.
It has the length for the hash and the salt.
All of that information is stored right inside.
There's no reason to have two things a salt and a password value in the database.
That's why the crypt is so fantastic.
The self is built in and there's nothing to worry about in terms of storing a separate value.
Now that we have this hash we can look at how to actually compare.
If this hash equals the plaintext password this is what we're going to do when someone logs in to illustrate
this.
I'm going to create a variable called hashed password.
I just copied the password to the clipboard.
I'm going to paste it inside of quotes right here and now we're going to try to compare this value to
the string.
One two three ABC.
Exclamation mark.
To compare values we're going to go ahead and use our final function off of B crypt.
This is B crypt dot.
Compare a B crypt dot compare takes the plane value the hash value and then it lets you know if those
two equal each other.
The first argument to compare is the plain string in our case we have our plane password stored in the
password variable.
The second argument is the hash value we have that in hashed password and the third argument that is
simply a callback function.
It might get a call with an error and it is going to get called with a result.
The result is either true or false it's true if the password matches the hash password and it's false.
If they do not equal each other.
Now we can finish off our aero function and we can go ahead and print the value of response to the screen
using console dialog.
R e s.
And we can comment out our previous calls to John salt and hash since we already have the hash value
right here.
Now I can say it hashing out J S and over inside of the terminal we can run the file.
I'm going to rerun the file.
And what do we get we get.
True we're getting true back because the password password 1 2 3 ABC exclamation mark does indeed equal
this hashed value.
Now if we were to change the password setting an equal to something else like 1 2 3 exclamation mark
without the ABC this is going to result in false.
If I rerun the file that's exactly what we get.
And this is what we're going to do when we loggin a user We're going to fetch the value out of the database
the hashed password value we're going to compare it to the plain text value they gave us and then we'll
be able to use this response variable to determine whether or not the password was correct.
Now that we know how to use be crypt we're going to add it inside of our user model.
We're going to be hashing all of our passwords before we save them.
Now in order to do this but we're going to explore is something called mongoose middleware mongoose
middleware lets you run certain code before or after certain events.
For example an update of that we can run some code before we update a model.
We can run some code after we update it.
In our case we want to run some code before a document is saved before we ever save that document to
the database.
We want to make sure the hashed password is in place to get this done we're going to explore the documentation
real quick so you know where it is.
There is a ton of middleware methods that we won't be using but you should know where they are mongoose
middleware is going to bring you to that documentation page.
Here we are we have the docs middleware page and up above they outline all of the different events.
We have an in it event validate save remove and countless others.
Well not countless But quite a few.
If you scroll down below you can get a quick idea about exactly how it works right here we have some
schema pretended it's our user schema and what we do is we attach an event user schema dot pre runs
the code before the event the event is saved.
And right here we actually run the code we call next when we're done and that is when the model gets
saved to the database.
This is exactly what we're going to do.
Only inside of the callback we're going to be hashing and the password to get this done we can pull
up Adam and we can start modifying our user schema down near the bottom of the file just below find
by token.
We're going to attach something else to user schema user schema the dot pre this is going to run some
code before a given event and the event we want to run code before is the save event before we ever
save the doc to the database.
We want to make some changes to it.
Now I am going to be using a regular function once again and because we are going to need access to
the this binding.
So I use the function keyword and this is going to get called with the next argument you have to provide
this argument and you have to call it somewhere inside of your function.
If you don't provide it and you don't call it the middleware is never going to complete and your program
is going to crash inside of here.
We're going to get access to the individual document much like we've got access to it up above and generate
auth token.
We created a variable lowercase U user and said equal to the value of this.
That's exactly what I'm going to do right here.
We're make a variable user setting an equal to this.
And now we can go ahead and check if the password was modified.
Now this is a really important thing.
There is going to be times where we save the document and we're never going to have updated the password
which means the password will already be hashed.
Imagine I saved a document with the plain text password then the password gets hashed.
Later on I update something that's not the password like the email.
This middleware is going to run again.
That means we're going to hash our hash and the program is going to break but we're going to do is use
a method available on our instance called user data is modified is modified takes an individual property
like password and it returns True or false returns true if password is modified it returns false if
it's not.
And we only want to encrypt the password.
If it was just modified which means we can wrap this inside of an IF condition if the user is password
modified function returns true.
We're going to go ahead and run some code.
This is where we're going to hash the password.
If it is not modified inside of the else statement we'll simply call next.
Moving on with the middleware.
Now if the password is modified This is where we want to add our two calls the call to gen's salt and
the call to hash before we can call either of them we do have to load them in up at the top of the file
just below load.
I'm going to create a new constant called B crypt and will require it just like we did in hashing J
J.S. require the B script J.
S now that we have an imported it's time for you to complete the rest.
This is going to be your challenge.
You already know how to create a salt and how to hash a password you have access to the password via
user password.
So instead of referencing the password variable like we do here you would reference user password.
Now once you have the hash value after you call decrypt hash you're going to set it on user dot password
user dot password is going to equal the hash value then you're going to go ahead and call.
Next you have to call next after you set that value.
Otherwise the middleware will never complete.
All you have to do is fill out the rest.
You have to call the genset function.
You have to call the hash function and inside of the callback for hash you have to add these two statements.
Once you're done want you to startup the server and make a call to sign up a new user inside of postman.
Once you have the call completed and you get a 200 You should be able to head into Roboam mango view
the record and you should see the hashed password as opposed to the plain text password.
Also feel free to wipe your database using robo Mongo since we do have users with plain text passwords
in there and it's a good idea to make sure that you don't have any old stray documents in there that's
going to cause any errors in the future.
Take a moment to knock this out.
Test it.
Make sure the stored password is to be hashed password and when you're done go ahead and click play.
How'd you do.
Hopefully you were able to integrate the B crypt algorithm into this middleware.
The first thing I'm going to do is generate a salt using be crypt dot Jeon salt and we're going to set
it up exactly like we did inside of our hashing File.
We're going to pass in 10 for the rounds and then we'll have our call back here.
We're going to get the actual salt value and we'll be able to use that to call hash.
Next up we are going to call hash B crypt dot hash passing in our three arguments the first being the
plain password which you have access to via user dot password.
The second being the salt.
We have that in the salt variable.
And the third being our callback function.
This is where we get the actual cash value.
Now once we have the hash value we're going to need to update the user document by setting user password
equal to the hash.
Remember the user password property was just equal to the plaintext passwords so we have to override
that in order to properly hide the plain text password then we're going to call next which is going
to complete the middleware and it'll move on it to save the document.
The next thing you needed to do after completing this was test it out over inside of the terminal going
to shut down at my server it already is shut down so I can move into Roboam mango and wipe my database
now back in the terminal I can start it up using node server server.
J.
And we can make a post man request over inside of post man.
I'm going to make a post user's request to sign up a new user and since I just wipe the database I can
use my default data right here.
Notice the plain password it's password followed by an exclamation mark.
Now when I send this off we still get to 200 and we can't quite tell if it worked or not because the
only data we get back is the ID and the email which hasn't changed based on the code we just wrote in
order to make sure the password is getting hashed.
I'm going to head over to Roboam mango refresh my connection to get access to that to do app database
and I'm going to explore the users collection inside of here.
I can view my documents.
I have one document and right here you see the hashed password and this is fantastic.
The plain text password is no longer in sight.
Instead we're storing the hashed password.
So if someone does get access to this value they're not going to be any closer towards getting the user's
password.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and make a commit over inside of the terminal.
I'm going to shut down the server run it get status and right here we have our three changed files.
I can then run get commit with the M flag to make a message a good message for this one as hash user
password before saving.
I'm going to make the commit push it up to get help and that is it for this one.
That is it for this one I will see you next time where we start testing those two routes.
We're going to kick things off by updating how we seed the database that's coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you then