Before we can actually test our two routes the Sign-Up route and the get users mi route.
We're going to need to add some seed data to the database for the users collection.
We're going to need to use that data in order to test things like authenticate if we want to make sure
this route works.
We're going to need to pass along an X or token inside a super test which means we're going to need
an Zaka token in the database in order for this call to work to set up our data.
We are going to kick things off by opening up server test ADOT J.S. but instead of adding more code
on here making this file more bloated than it already is we're going to create a separate file that's
responsible for creating the seed data and defining the function that gets passed to before each before
we add anything new.
We're simply going to migrate this functionality over to the new file.
Then we can verify it still works.
Then we'll move on adding a user sead data.
First up I am going to run the test suite using NPM test to prove that all my test cases are still working.
Then we're going to make the change moving this to a new file and we'll run NPM test again to make sure
we haven't broken anything.
Now this new file is going to live in the Test folder.
We're going to make a new folder called seed and inside of the seed folder it will make a file called
SEE THE DOT J s inside of here.
We're going to add the code we have over in server test.
J.S. at the very top of the file the first thing we want to grab is that to Doo's array.
This array is going to be added to the database.
I'm going to cut it out of the server file and paste it in here.
Next up we are going to be grabbing the function that gets passed to before each.
We're not going to grab the actual before each call just the function.
Now over in server doc J.S. we can define a new function.
Let's make a contest called populate to do's and we'll set that equal to the function we've just copied.
Now we have everything divined over in the seed file as opposed to the server file.
We're not quite done yet.
We do need to load in some imports.
We use the object id constructor and we also access it need to do a model.
That means up at the top of the file We're going to have to add two lines.
First up let's go ahead and load in the object id constructor function.
We'll make a cons object id using E.S. 60 structuring just like we've done before.
Make sure you spell it right though and then we'll go ahead and require it off of a mango D-B.
Next up we're going to go ahead and load in that to do model because we do call to do not remove and
to do not insert many to modify the collection we'll make a concert.
We'll call that Konst to do using yes 6 destructuring and we will go ahead and require it using a relative
path.
Now we are in the tests ceed a directory which means we're going to need to go up to directories out
of seed and out of tests then we'll go into models.
That means we'll use dot dot to go up one directory and dot dot again to go up a second directory.
And now we can go ahead and reference the models directory.
And finally the file to do now that we have both of our imports in place.
The last thing to do is export the Dewes array since we do use that in the server test file down below
we access it inside of our test cases and we're also going to export the function we just defined populate
to do's module Boddam exports is going to equal an object and on there we'll add those two things to
do's and populate to do.
Excellent with our experts in place.
The seed file is done and we can move into the server test file to load in the seed data right here
just below where I require the to do model.
I am going to go ahead and use a constant.
And we're going to pull off a few of those properties.
We're going to pull off the two do's array and we're going to pull off populate days.
We're going to grab all of that from the file we just created using require.
We'll use a relative path since it is a local file.
It's in the seed directory on the file name itself is called seed.
Now we don't need to do anything with it to do array.
We simply reference it down below like we did before and everything works as expected.
But we are going to need to pass in populate to do's right here.
With this in place.
We have not changed a single piece of functionality we've just refactored our program to move some code
out of server tasks and in to the seed file.
Now that we've made this change I am going to rerun the test suite to verify that everything is still
working as expected here all 11 Tests are passing which means we're ready to move on adding some seed
data for that users collection in order to see the users we are going to create a users array much like
we did for dues and we'll also make a populate users function much like we did for dues down below.
First up let's go ahead and load in the user model.
We'll make a concert called user and we're going to require it using a very similar path.
It's a relative path.
We're going to go back those two directories then into models.
And finally the user file is what we want to grab now that we have this in place we can define a constant
called users.
And this is going to be the array the array of users we add as our seed data.
We're going to add to users so I'm going to add two objects to the array.
The first user this is going to be a user with a valid authentication token.
And the second user is going to be a user that does not have any authentication tokens and will use
the second user for things like testing.
What happens when we don't pass an X auth token.
For now though we can start filling out these users the first one is going to have an underscore ID
property.
We're going to set that equal to a new object ID then we can set up an email on a password.
A good email for this one would be Andrew at example dot com.
And finally that password field I'm going to set password equal to user 1 pass.
Next up we are going to need to provide the tokens array.
Remember the tokens array is an array of objects and every object has two properties access and token.
The access property is easy enough.
We simply set access equal to the string off but the token property is going to be a little more difficult.
The token property is going to require us to call JWT sign just like we do over inside of user.
J.S. down below.
Right here we sign our data creating the token we're going to need to do the exact same thing using
the exact same secret.
ABC 1 2 3 in order to create the seed data.
Now we are going to need to reference the user ID inside of that call and since we've provided it right
here there's no way to reference it.
So instead what I'm going to do is make a variable a constant called user 1 ID and I'm going to set
that equal to the object id that I can reference this wherever I want.
Down below I'm going to pass it in right here.
User 1 ID and I'm going to pass it into our call to JWT dot sign.
And before I can call that function I am going to load it in concert JWT and we're going to require
the Jason Webb token library.
Now we can call JWT that sign passing in the necessary arguments for the data that we want to sign and
we're going to have our two values the ID which we have access to via the user one ID variable and access
which as we know we're just going to set equal to the string off.
Next up we are going to need to go ahead and provide the exact same secret we used earlier.
The secret we used was ABC 1 2 3.
So I'm going to provide that as the second argument.
I'm also going to wrap up this call by calling to string converting this into the string token.
Now that we have the first user in place we can go ahead and at our second user and the second user
is going to be a lot more simple we're not going to have to add the tokens array.
I am going to make a variable to store its ID though a Konst user to ID variable and we'll set that
equal to a new object.
Now down below we can add the three attributes necessary ID email and password Id obviously will equal
the variable we just created the email can equal any info that we haven't used we only used one.
So I'm going to go ahead and use Jen an example dot com.
And finally we can provide a password and I want to stick with that same scheme for the password property
I used use or one pass for this one.
I will use user to pass down below.
Now we have our users created and it's time to start actually populating the database.
We're going to do that via a function really similar to populate to do.
There's one important caveat though.
Insert many is what we currently use to insert our records into the database.
But this is not going to run our middleware which means when we insert these records the plain text
password is going to get stored in the database.
Obviously that's going to cause some problems later and we try to test things because our tests are
going to assume the password was properly hashed in order to save these users and have the password
hashed.
We're going to tweak how we create our populate user's function.
Konst populate users is going to be the name of the function and we are going to set it equal to an
arrow function that gets the Done argument just like we do for populate to do's up above now inside
of popular users things are going to start in much the same.
We're going to wipe all of the users in the database by calling user remove and we're going to pass
in that empty object to remove every single record.
Then we'll tack on a then callback and inside of here is where we're going to actually add the records.
I'm going to add this missing semicolon and now we can go ahead and start by creating those users.
The first thing I'm going to do is make a variable called User 1 and we're going to set this equal to
a new user and we're going to pass in the object that is the first item in the user's array.
We can get that by accessing the first item using the zero index.
Then we can go ahead and call Save on this.
And the value that gets returned from Save that is what's going to be in User 1.
And as we know that is a promise which means we can tack on then and we'll be using that in just a moment
to sync things up.
We're going to do the exact same thing for a user to a VAR user 2 equals a new user.
We're going to grab the second item from the array with the index of one and we'll be calling Save getting
the promise back.
Now we have two promises user 1 and user two we want to wait for both of them to succeed.
And there's actually a promise utility method that lets you do just that.
It's called Promise.
The dot all promised dot all takes an array of promises.
We can pass in our array.
User 1 and user 2.
Then we can call then and this call back it's not going to get fired until all of those promises resolve.
Meaning that user one end user to were successfully saved to the database by calling save.
We are going to be running the middleware and by using promised to all we'll be able to wait for all
of those save actions to complete.
Now I'm going to go ahead and remove the then call back here and instead I'll return the promise.
All result.
So I can tack on then right here right here.
All I'm going to do is do what we did above.
I get a call done wrapping up the populate to Dewes middleware function.
Now with this in place we are done we can go ahead and run our test suite and see exactly what kind
of data we get over in a rowboat Mongo.
Now over inside of robo Monga we have some weird data inside of the test file inside of collections
I have left over user data.
I'm going to go ahead and drop this to do app test database.
This will get recreated when we run the test suite over inside of Adam.
I'm going to save the seed file and I am going to be adding a second before each call over inside of
a server test.
First up though I do need to export populate users and I need to export the users array up above.
Right here we're going to export users and will export populate users and over inside of our server
test file.
We can add both of those as Constance users.
Populate users and will pass populate users in to a second call to before each.
I'm going to add the second call before populate to Doo's populate users.
Excellent.
Now that we have this in place we can rerun any test suite all of the tests should pass.
We haven't actually changed any of the test cases.
The real goal for rerunning the test suite is to see what kind of data we have in the test database.
Once the test cases are complete over in Roboam ongo I'm going to refresh my connection go into the
to do app test database and see what I have inside of the users collection inside of here.
I have two records.
The first one looks exactly like our second record.
We have Jannette example adcom we have our ID and we have our hashed password.
Notice there's nothing in the tokens array.
The second record is the first item we have in the user's array.
Right here we have our ID our e-mail the hash password and we also have art Hogan this token is going
to be used inside of our test case to run those tests that require authentication.
With this in place we are now done.
We have a really great seed file the seed file abstracts all of that seed related functionality and
doesn't need to live in server test where it was just taking up space.
Now that we had this in place it's time to move on and actually write test cases that use this data
that's coming up next so stay tuned.
I will see you then.