Now that we have our user data in the test database we can actually write those test cases for the two
routes we've created.
This is going to happen in the bottom of the server test file.
We'll be doing some of them together and some of them will be challenges.
First up let's test the route that returns the individual authenticated user will make a new described
block for a get users.
Me and right in here we're going to add two test cases one and when we have a valid authentication token
and one when we do not provide an authentication token so we can make sure the private route is indeed
private.
First up it should return a user if authenticated.
This one is going to be an asynchronous test like all of the previous ones.
So I will be adding the Dunn argument inside of our callback function.
And the second test case it should return a 4.
0 1 if not authenticated and this task is going to make sure that when no token is provided Random User
Data is not sent back to someone who shouldn't have access to it we're going to do the first test case
together and you'll be responsible for setting up the second one up here.
The first thing we're going to do is make the request to the application using super test.
This is going to be a GET request and the request doesn't require any special you Arel parameters it
simply forward slash users forward slash meat.
Next up we're going to set a header and this is something we haven't done before to set in super test.
We use the set method set takes two arguments and he had her name as the first one and he had her value
is the second one in our case the header name is going to be X off and the header value is going to
be this value right here at the token value inside of the first user.
We're going to go into the users array.
We're going to grab the first item we're going to go into it's tokens array they grab the first item
and access the dot token property.
Now that we have our headers set we can start making some assertions about what should happen we should
get back 200 as the age TTP status code.
We can expect a 200 to come back and we can also go ahead and expect some things about the body that
comes back.
I'm going to expect and I get to pass in a custom expect function and then here we're going to make
a few assertions.
First up let's assert the ID equals the appropriate ID.
I'm going to expect that the response a body id property equals using to be the ID we have here for
the first user.
That means inside of to be I'm going to pass in user's printer grab the first one we're going to grab
the id property and we're going to call two hacks string.
Excellent.
Now this should be the case when we're fetching a user ID that comes back in the body should be the
idea of the user whose token we supplied.
Next up we can go ahead and assert that the e-mails match.
I'm going to expect that the response body e-mail property equals using it to be the following.
We're going to go into that user's array and grab the first item then we just need to access the e-mail
property like this.
And there we go.
We have two assertions that make sure when we provide a valid token we get valid data back.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and tack on a call to end passing in done just like we've
done in the past with this in place.
Our test case is now ready to go.
We can run it from the terminal using NPM test when I run it.
We should now see we have 12 test cases and all 12 are passing.
It's going through the to do test cases right now.
Now we're going through the user's me and we do indeed get the appropriate data.
Now the second task that we haven't filled out that one fails because we never call the done function.
That's perfectly fine.
For now this means everything is working as expected.
If the email that comes back is something else I'm going to concatenate the number one and we rerun
the test suite.
We are going to see that test failing because the e-mail that came back on the body which we modified
just to prove a point doesn't equal the e-mail that we added as the seed data right here.
You can see the test case does indeed fail.
I'm going to go ahead and revert that change so it passes again and we can move on to the second function
and this is going to be your first challenge.
Your challenge here is to make a call to the users.
Me Around the same and get request you're not going to provide an X auth token and all you're gonna
do is expect that you get a 401.
Back.
You're also going to expect that the body is equal to an empty object which it should be if the user
is not authenticated.
Once you have both of those assertions in place make sure to call and passing and done.
This is going to wrap up the test case.
And remember also when you're comparing an empty object which is going to be the response body to another
object you have to use to equal not to be take a moment to knock this out.
Go ahead and run the test suite make sure both tests under get users me are passing when they are go
ahead and click play.
All right.
Hopefully you were able to add that test case and see it pass over in the terminal.
First up we got to make the request.
Nothing new here.
Request to the app and we're going to make the exact same request a get request to forward Sodje users
forward slash to me.
And this time around that we will not be calling said we want to see what happens when we don't provide
the token we can make our assertions.
We're expecting a 401.
Which is the status code we send back from in the authenticates middleware and then we can go ahead
and make a custom assertion about the body we can pass in the response argument to our custom callback
function and we can expect that the response body is an empty object which it should be.
We should not have any user properties on it.
I'm going to expect response dot body to equal that object just like this.
Now we can tack on end passing end done in our test case is complete if we don't get a 401.
The test is going to fail if the body includes anything except for an empty object.
The test is going to fail as well.
Over inside of the terminal I'm going to rerun the test suite.
We should now have 13 tests and all of them should be passing and through the to do tests right now.
And we should be getting on to the users tests and there we go.
Both tests are passing which is fantastic.
Now that we have some test cases for the get users mirror outlets go ahead and add some test cases for
the Sign-Up route.
We're going to add three.
But first up we have to add our describe block and the route for this is a post to request to forward
slash users that I can provide my function and inside of here we can add three test cases.
Let's go ahead and call it three times first then we'll worry about the actual test cases it should
create a user.
This call is going to test what happens when we pass in a valid data a valid e-mail that's not already
in use.
Any valid password we should have the user created.
Next up we can test what happens when the fields are invalid it should return validation errors if request
invalid.
And this one is going to make sure that when we provide either an invalid e-mail or a password that's
not at least six characters the user doesn't get created.
The last test.
We're going to write for the sign up method.
It should not create user if e-mail in use.
If the email is already in use we do not want to create the user.
So we're going to write a test case that verifies We do indeed get the error.
Excellent.
Now that we have all the test cases set up let's go ahead and fill out the first one.
This first test case is going to require that we have a unique valid e-mail and a password.
I'm going to make those two variables up above e-mail which all set equal to.
Example at example dot com and password which all set equal to a valid password such as 1 to 3 AM and
B.
Exclamation mark.
Next up we can actually send off the request using a request passing in our app and this one is going
to be a post request.
So I'll call the post method now that you are off this one is not going to be dynamic so we can use
a regular string as opposed to a template string.
And we're going to forward slash users.
This is the route for creating a new user and we are going to need to send some data along with this
request and this is the one that makes sure everything works when we send valid data.
So I will be calling send passing in both the email and password on our object.
Email is going to get the value from the e-mail variable above and we'll do the same thing for password.
Now that we have the request sent off we can start making some assertions about what should happen.
First up we are expecting a 200 it to be the status code that comes back that we can go ahead and expect
that we get our X auth token back using a custom expect call.
We're expecting that the following function doesn't throw any errors.
I'm going to expect that the response headers object has a header called X off.
And in order to get the value we're going to need to use the bracket notation as opposed to the dot
notation because our header name and does have a hyphen in it which would be invalid using dot notation.
Right here though inside of the single quotes we can provide the name x.
We're expecting this value to exist.
We don't really care what it is we just want to make sure it does exist when the user is created.
Next up we can go ahead and verify that there is an e-mail and there is an ID.
I'm going to expect that their response a body has an ID.
We expect the I.D. to exist and we can do the exact same thing for the e-mail.
We're expecting the response abody e-mail property to be the value up above.
Instead of using to exist we can specify the actual value since we know it now that we have this in
place we can go ahead and call and passing in done.
I can save the file and we can run our test case and make sure everything works as expected.
I'm going to rerun the entire test suite.
We should now have 14 passing tests
going through the to do's tests now we're in the users tests and we do indeed have a passing test should
create a user passes.
Now the other tests are failing but that's expected.
We haven't filled those ones out.
Now if you want we can take this test case even a little further.
Instead of passing and done and we could pass in one of our custom functions this is going to let us
query the database making sure everything looks good there like we've done in other custom and functions.
We're going to check if there's an error if there is an error we're simply going to call.
Done.
Return done.
Passing in the error.
So the test fails if there is no errors in the assertions.
Up above we can go ahead and query for a user.
I'm going to use user dot find one to find a user where the email equals the email we have above.
This should indeed return a valid user since we just created it and got a 200 back then I can add on
then we're going to get the user and we can make some assertions about the document saved in the database.
For example we could expect it exists I'm going to expect that the user exists using to exist.
We could even expect that the password does not equal the password we used since it should have been
hashed.
We can expect that the user password property does not equal using.
To not be the password variable defined above.
If the user password is equal to the password above we have a pretty big problem because that means
our passwords are not getting hashed right after my two expect calls.
I can call done wrapping up this test case.
Now that we have this in place I can rerun the test suite and that test should still be passing this
time around though it is fetching the actual user from the database and it's making some assertions
about the document right here moving through all the tests and the first test is failing.
Should create a user is not passing.
Let's go ahead and see what the error is and try to fix it.
User is not defined.
That's an easy one.
When you get errors like this it usually means you forgot to do something basic like importing the correct
library up above all I need to do to fix that error.
This create a constant call user and require the user model forward slash.
We're going to go back a directory into the models directory and we're going to grab the user file.
Now that we have this in place I should be able to save the server test file.
Rerun the test suite and our test case right here should be passing.
I'm going to rerun it to make sure the error was fixed and if it was we can move on to the to final
test cases for this one.
We're going through the to do tests now we're out the user's tests and the first test passes which is
fantastic.
All that's left to do is fill out those final two test cases and this is going to be your second challenge
for this one.
All you need to do is send across an invalid email and an invalid password.
You expect 400 to come back if it does then everything is working as expected for the second one you're
going to go ahead and use an email that's already taken.
Which means that you're going to try to sign up using one of the emails that we use in our seed data.
Either Andrew an example dot com Gen at example dot com or if you happen to name something else go ahead
and use that instead.
This request the second one should also fail when you have an email that's already in use and a valid
password you're going to expect a 400 to come back.
For that take a moment to knock both of those out.
Make sure you get 400 for both.
When you're done run the test suite make sure all the tests are passing.
Then go ahead and click play.
Hopefully you were able to get these two tests complete and passing over inside of the terminal.
The first test were going to run is going to be the one that has an invalid email and an invalid password.
I'm going to request something from the application.
We're going to go ahead and make a post request to the exact same u r l we used above forward slash
users in lower case then we're going to go ahead and send across some data.
I'll provide my object which is going to be the data we send and it will send an email equal to an invalid
email like and and will send a password which is also invalid.
Like one two three.
Both of these are invalid so we can start making some assertions about what we're going to get back.
We're going to expect that we get a 400 back and then we can go ahead and call end passing done this
test case should now pass.
If everything goes as expected I'm going to save the server test file and restart the test suite over
inside of the terminal.
This time around we only have that one test case failing the one we just filled out should indeed be
passing where moving through that to do tasks.
Now we're in the users tests and it's passing which is great.
We can now move on to the final test.
This test makes sure that when we try to sign up a user but that emails are already in use we get a
400 back.
I'm going to kick things off by calling request to initialize the request.
We will be making a post request it to the exact same you are l forward slash users.
And now we can go ahead and set up our data in site of Send Now the data for this test case is supposed
to be valid.
It's just supposed to be already in use which means for the email we want to use one of the emails in
our users array.
I'm going to go ahead and access the first item in the user's array.
I'm going to grab the email and I'm going to use that right here and this email is obviously already
in the database since it's part of our seed data so we should get a 400 back for the password.
I'm going to set it equal to a valid password like password one two three exclamation mark.
Next up we can make our assertion expecting that a 400 comes back.
I'm going to expect that we get a 400 and then I can call and passing in done and we can rerun the test
suite for a final time this time around.
We should have all 16 test cases passing if we do.
We're done we can wrap up the video by making a commit right here we're moving on to the user's tasks
and it looks like everything did work as expected which is fantastic.
Now that we have some test cases in place for the sign up call and the get users Mikol Let's go ahead
and make a commit to save the changes.
I'm going to run get status and right here we have our new seed file as well as our modified server
test file.
I can usually get added to add all of those to the next commit and get commit with the M flag for a
message add tests for get users me and post users.
Excellent.
Now that we have this in place we are done.
I'm going to push things up to get help and that is it for this one.
I will see you in the next video where we keep moving through the process of adding authentication to
the to do API