In this video you're going to set up a dedicated route for logging in existing users.
Currently the only way you can get an x token back is on the Sign-Up call.
If you lose the token or you sign in from a different device obviously you're going to want to be able
to get a new one.
And currently that is just not possible.
You can't make another call to the post users route because the email already exists.
So the call is going to return a 400.
What we need is a dedicated route for logging in users.
Now Double-O this is going to be a post route and you are all we're going to use for this is forward
slash users forward slash log in when you make a POST request to this route you'll be sending along
some data you're going to send along an email in the request body and also the plain text password.
This means that we're going to need to try to find a user in the Mongo DB user's collection who one
has an e-mail matching the e-mail sent in and two has a hashed password that equals the plain text password
when passed through the B crypt compare method which we used over inside of our hashing js file right
here.
We used to be crypt compare to compare a plain text value with a hash value.
That's exactly what we're going to be doing to get this call to work and setting up this route is going
to be your first challenge.
I want you to set up this route then pick off the email and the password from the request body and to
verify that the route is set up correctly.
You can simply go ahead and respond using response send.
And you can send back the body data then invite you to fire up your server.
Make the log in call in postman passing in an e-mail and a password and make sure you get the e-mail
and password back.
Take a moment to knock this out test it and when you're done go ahead and click play.
All right to get this done.
But I'm going to do is call app drop post.
We want to set up that post route.
Now I can provide to you r l forward slash users forward slash log in.
Now this is going to be a standard express route.
We're not going to be using the authenticate middleware because you don't have a token.
You're trying to get one that's the whole purpose of this call.
We're going to have the request and response arguments inside of our callback function.
And the first thing we're going to do is pick off the e-mail and the password.
Now we've written this line before there's no reason to rewrite it.
I can simply copy and paste it down below.
Now the last thing I wanted you to do just to make sure the data was getting picked off properly is
simply respond response send sending back the abody.
Then we can go ahead and start up our server.
I'm going to use gnomon to do that.
No Amaan server.
Forward slash server.
SJS once the server is up and you see you're started at port three thousand message you can move over
to postman and actually make a log in request.
I'm going to make a post request to the local that you are all I can inject the you are allright here.
Forward slash users forward slash log in.
Then I'm going to send somebody data along as well.
This is going to be Jason data.
We're going to provide our two properties inside of our adjacent object.
First up is going to be the e-mail I'm going to set this to Andrew at example dot com and a password
which I'll set to whatever I like.
1 2 3 ABC Act.
Now that I have this in place I can go ahead and send off my request and down below I do indeed get
the data back.
I have the e-mail and the password is not showing up below because I mis spelt it up above.
If I go ahead and spell it correctly I now get the password.
Also if you have this in place then you're ready to move on actually filling out the route.
Now the first thing we need to do is verify that a user exists with that e-mail.
Then we're going to go ahead and get it's password property and pass that through the crypt compare.
Now all of this is going to happen inside of a nother model method.
We're going to create a model method just like we have in users.
We have an existing model method it is called Find by tokin.
We're going to make a separate one called find by credentials.
This is going to take the email and password as arguments.
It's then going to do its thing returning a promise with a user or with an error if the user didn't
exist.
Right here we can define that method user schema ADOT statics for a model method and this one will be
called Find a by credentials now find by credentials.
As I mentioned is going to take two arguments and I am going to use the function keyword because we
do need access to this binding as we have for all of our other methods right here.
We're going to have our e-mail argument as well as our password argument then we can go ahead and set
up the function.
And now we can call it over inside of server.
I'm going to call it so I know kind of how I want it to work before I actually fill it out over here.
Inside of server.
Yes we can essentially call and find how it's going to work.
This is a strategy I use pretty often.
I'd like to write my method call first so I can figure out exactly what I want the method to do.
Then I go ahead and write the method to fit my needs.
In this case my needs are the ability to pass and email and password and get the user back user ADOT
find by credentials is going to be the method it will be calling and will be passing in the body email
property as well as the body password property.
Next up what I like to be able to do is add a call to then once we find the user the success case should
get that user back.
And right here is where we would go ahead and create a new token responding to the HTP request.
Now if we're not able to find a user that's fine too I'm going to add a catch call.
We're getting at that error argument and right here is where we can respond to the user letting them
know that we were not able to log in.
Now before I go any further I am going to go ahead and actually define defined by credentials.
I know how I want it to work.
And now it's time to fill the method out inside of here.
One of the first things we need to do is simply try to find a user where the e-mail equals of the e-mail
that was passed in.
Now it would be nice if we could do that via email and password but unfortunately we can't remember
we have the plain text password.
We do not have the password actually stored in the database so we can't simply query the data in order
to find a potential match.
We're going to find the user that does have the email of the email passed in.
Now that is going to be nothing new here we're going to make a variable uppercase U user setting an
equal to this.
This is exactly what we did for our find by token method.
And then we can go ahead and make a call to user ADOT find one.
We're going to try to find a one user the user whose email matches the email we have right here.
That means inside of our query all we have to do is reference e-mail like this.
This is going to set an email property equal to the e-mail variable.
Now I am going to be returning this we're going to be changing this promise since I added a then call
and a catch call over here in server J S and N here we are going to tack on a then call because there
is still more work to be done.
We're not quite done we have to verify that the password also matches all of that is going to happen
inside of here.
Now we might get a user we might not.
Either way we are going to specify the user argument.
If we don't get a user we want to do something different we don't want to try to compare passwords since
there is no password to compare.
If there is no user what are we going to do.
We're simply going to return a rejected premise.
This is going to automatically trigger the catch case over here in server Yes and we can respond with
an error.
Now back inside of user dot J.S. we are going to return a call to promise dot reject.
Excellent.
Now we already handled the case where the user doesn't exist it's time to move on and figure out what
to do when a user does exist.
No the problem we're going to run into here is that the B script method we're going to be using be script
doc compare it only supports callbacks in fact all of the script JS library methods only support callbacks.
They do not support promises.
I want to keep using promises I've been using them through the whole app.
They're my preferred way to make a synchronous code work.
So what I'm going to do instead is return a new promise like we did in previous sections here we're
going to provide our function.
We can either call resolve if it's a success we can call reject if it's not a success.
And in here we can do whatever we like in our case.
The thing that we're going to do in here is use decrypt dot compare to compare the password right here
with the user data password property.
Now that means over inside of server J as we are going to be able to do something with the user when
it comes back.
For the moment we're going to do is respond with the user response send something in the user that got
found.
Now notice here I'm not using an if statement to check if user exists or not.
We created defined by credentials method so we get to determine how it works.
If there is no user the catch case is going to get fired.
That's exactly what we did when we set up this if statement right here.
Back inside of server J s inside of catch.
We're going to respond with a 400 status enemy to go ahead and call send to send the response.
Now with this in place we're not quite done in terms of what we're going to add to server.
Yes we do still need to create an authentication tokin that's going to happen in a few minutes.
But for now we have enough in server Jay asks where her challenge can be to complete the find by credentials
method right here.
You're going to use be crypt doc compair use decrypt dot compare to compare password and user dot password.
If the result is true that means you did find a user and you can call resolve with the user.
We found it right here if the result is false meaning that the password and the hash password are not
matches you can just call the reject method which we have defined right here and that will trigger the
catch case over inside of server.
J.S. that means all you really need to put inside of here where the comment is is the compare call just
like we have over inside of our hashing file instead of logging out the response you're going to go
ahead and check if it's true or false.
If it's true you'll call resolved with the user if it's false.
You're going to call reject.
Take a moment to knock that out.
And then I want you to test it as well.
Now you can feel free to completely wipe your robo Mongo database.
Then inside a post man you can make a new user then you can try to log in with those exact same credentials
and what you should get back is the user object since we send it back right here.
Then I'd also like you to mess up either the e-mail or the password and make sure you get a 400 back.
So take a moment to try to knock this out.
Feel free to use anything we've done in any of our projects to solve this problem.
When you're done test it make sure everything works as expected.
Then you can go ahead and click play how that go.
I know that one was a little tricky but hopefully you were able to get it done and you were able to
test it inside of postman.
The first thing I'm going to do is call the crypt dot compare that we've already used be crypt in this
file.
We used it when we created our account.
So there is no reason to go ahead and import it again it's already up there down inside of the challenge
area.
We can now pass in the three necessary arguments.
The first one as we know is the plain password and we have access to that is via the argument password.
Next up we have to pass in the hashed password and this is available on user ADOT password.
And the final argument is our callback function with our two arguments now inside of here we need to
check if the value of response is true or false.
If the response variable is true we want to go ahead and resolve this promise.
We want to resolve it with the user.
This is going to let us do stuff with the user over inside of server J s like we do right here.
If the result variable is not true we can add an else clause in that case.
We're going to simply call a project rejecting the promise and this is going to send a four hundred
back with this in place we're ready to test that everything is working as expected.
I'm going to save the file and inside of robo Mongo I'm going to go ahead and wipe the to do app collection
so I can recreate my users inside of post man.
Then inside a post man we can go ahead and make a sign up request.
I'm going to create that in a new tab.
We can just click our post users request over inside of our collection sidebar and I am going to check
out the data because I need to use these exact same credentials in just a few minutes.
Here we have an example dot com as the email and we have password exclamation mark as the password.
Now I can send off this request.
This is going to create a new account.
We get our ID in our email and we get our X off hetter over here.
The goal now is to use these exact same credentials over inside our log in request up above.
I'm going to go ahead and change the password.
The email is already correct.
I'm going to change it to password exclamation mark and we can send off this request.
And what do we get down below.
We get a status of 200 and we get the user object back which is fantastic.
Notice here we are getting the exact same user the ID matches the ID we have inside of our response
body for the sign up call.
Now that we have this in place we can go ahead and test what happens when we send a bad password like
password without an exclamation mark.
In that case we get to 400.
We can also try to fetch a user whose email doesn't even exist.
If I send that off what do we get.
We could have 400 as well.
Now I'm going to change this back to the working example and we can go ahead and save this request.
If I send it off I can verify everything is working as expected and I'm going to add it to my to do
app collection.
We're going to use the same scheme we've been using for all of our routes and we're going to go ahead
and save them into the same collection.
And with this in place we are ready to move on to the very final step.
The final step inside of Adam is going to be to actually generate a new token and send it back and we're
going to use the exact same generate auth token method.
There is no reason to create a new one.
This is why we created the method in the first place we created it to be reusable.
Right here inside of our success case for when we do find the user we instead of actually responding
are going to call user dot generate auth token and then we can go ahead and tack on a then call back.
And then here will be getting the new token that was just created.
Now with this in place we can go ahead and return.
This is going to keep the chain alive so if we do run into any errors inside of the callback right here
the 400 will be used as the response inside of year the only thing we need to do is respond and we're
going to respond in a literally the exact same way responded up above.
So much so that I can actually take the line copy it and paste it down below.
Right inside of generate auth token here we use response header to set the X off after we set it equal
to the token.
We just generated and finally send the response body back as the user which we were already doing with
this in place we can now save server J S for the final time and test that everything works as expected
over inside of postman.
What we need to do is make another log and request one that is valid and down here inside of headers.
We should now have the X auth value.
I can take this value and make a request to get users me to verify that it is indeed a valid token.
I'm gonna head over to the users meet request and swap out the X auth token value for the one I just
copied it to the clipboard.
I'm going to send it off and right down here we get the user back which is fantastic.
This means that the log in call is indeed working the token it sends back does work with our other private
routes.
Now that we have this in place we are done with a log in route in the next video we're going to write
some test cases for the log in route.
But for now we are done we can go ahead and wrap this one up by making a commit.
I'm going to make sure all my atom files are saved.
It looks like they are over inside of the terminal I can now shut down gnomon and run get status.
Here we have our two changed files as expected which means we can go ahead and use get commit with the
EM flag and a good message for this one would be ADD post users log in route.
I'm going to make the commit push it up to get hub and that is it for this one.
I will see you next time where we test the route we just created.